<!-- chapter user-guide -->
  <chapter>
    <title>The Ring Buffer</title>
    <section>
      <title>Overview</title>

      <para>
        A ring buffer is a fundamental component of the system NSCLDAQ uses to
        pass data from one process to another. It is basically just a piece of
        memory that is accessible to multiple processes. Access is however
        controlled in such a way that only one process can contribute data to it
        while many processes can read from it. There is only allowed to be a
        single producer per ring buffer while there may be any number of
        consumers.
      </para>

      <para>
        Ring buffers are local to a specific computer but are accessible
        over the network. Each ring buffer is identified by a user-defined name
        and the hostname of the computer it is located on. When processes want to
        attach to a ring to either produce or consume its data, they must specify
        the name of the ring via a universal resource identifier (URI). The URI
        specifies the protocol (<literal>proto://</literal>), the hostname
        (<literal>host</literal>), and the name of the ring
        (<literal>name</literal>) as a single string:
        <literal>proto://host/name</literal>. Ring buffers can be accessed by
        using either the ring:// or tcp:// protocols (they are identical). When a
        user attaches to a ring on another computer, a service running in the
        background called <literal>RingMaster</literal> sets up the connection
        that will stream the data across the network for you. In this way, the
        nework is basically transparent.
      </para>

      <para>
        Sometimes it is useful to know what ring buffers exist. You can
        determine this using the <command>ringbuffer status</command>
        command. Doing so might produce the following ouput:
      </para>

      <screen>
<literal>spdaqxx&gt;</literal> <command>ringbuffer status</command>
+-----+------------+-------+-------------+--------+---------+---------+------+-------------+
|Name |data-size(k)|free(k)|max_consumers|producer|maxget(k)|minget(k)|client|clientdata(k)|
+-----+------------+-------+-------------+--------+---------+---------+------+-------------+
|0400x|8194        |8194   |100          |26550   |0        |0        |-     |-            |
|-    |-           |-      |-            |-       |-        |-        |26552 |0            |
|test |8194        |8194   |100          |-1      |0        |0        |-     |-            |
+-----+------------+-------+-------------+--------+---------+---------+------+-------------+
    </screen>
    <para>
      The leftmost column of the table specifies the name of the ring
      buffers on the system. Only rows with names other than "-" are
      actually ring buffers. Here you see there are two rings whose
      names are 0400x and test. The middle row that has a name entry of
      "-" is actually a row containing information for a client or
      consumer process attached to the 0400x ring buffer. The number in
      the client column is the pid of the consumer process. The producer column
      of the 0400x and test rows specify the pid of process except that it
      is for the producer process. You can see that the 0400x
      ring has a producer process with pid 26550, whereas the test ring
      has no producer process (pid=-1). Note also that the test
      ring buffer also does not have any consuming processes.
    </para>
    <para>
      You can create a new ring buffer whose name is "myring" by typing:
    </para>
    <screen>
<literal>spdaqxx&gt;</literal> <command>ringbuffer create myring</command>
<literal>spdaqxx&gt;</literal> <command>ringbuffer status</command>
+------+------------+-------+-------------+--------+---------+---------+------+-------------+
|Name  |data-size(k)|free(k)|max_consumers|producer|maxget(k)|minget(k)|client|clientdata(k)|
+------+------------+-------+-------------+--------+---------+---------+------+-------------+
|0400x |8194        |8194   |100          |26550   |0        |0        |-     |-            |
|-     |-           |-      |-            |-       |-        |-        |26552 |0            |
|myring|8194        |8194   |100          |-1      |0        |0        |-     |-            |
|test  |8194        |8194   |100          |-1      |0        |0        |-     |-            |
+------+------------+-------+-------------+--------+---------+---------+------+-------------+
    </screen>

    <para>
      You can clearly see that this create a brand new ring buffer on
      the system. Likewise, you can also delete ringbuffers. In general
      it is best to only delete them when there are no consuming
      processes. For illustration, I will delete the ring I just
      created.
    </para>
    <screen>
<literal>spdaqxx&gt;</literal> <command>ringbuffer delete myring</command>
<literal>spdaqxx&gt;</literal> <command>ringbuffer status</command>
+-----+------------+-------+-------------+--------+---------+---------+------+-------------+
|Name |data-size(k)|free(k)|max_consumers|producer|maxget(k)|minget(k)|client|clientdata(k)|
+-----+------------+-------+-------------+--------+---------+---------+------+-------------+
|0400x|8194        |8194   |100          |26550   |0        |0        |-     |-            |
|-    |-           |-      |-            |-       |-        |-        |26552 |0            |
|test |8194        |8194   |100          |-1      |0        |0        |-     |-            |
+-----+------------+-------+-------------+--------+---------+---------+------+-------------+
    </screen>

    <para>
      The only other thing that is worth mentioning is that ring buffers
      can be reset to an initial state. This process is called
      formatting the ring buffer. It is done very analogously to the
      creation and deletion commands.
    </para>

    <screen>
<literal>spdaqxx&gt;</literal> <command>ringbuffer format myring</command>
    </screen>

    <para>
      You may wonder why this is useful. Well, it is typically only
      useful if the producing process for the ring buffer exits badly.
      As you can see, each ring buffer keeps track of the processes that
      are are attached to it. Usually when one of these processes
      terminates, the ring buffer updates its records. However, if one
      of these processes exits uncleanly (e.g. segmentation fault), the
      ring may not properly get notified causing it to think that the
      now nonexistent process is still attached to it. For consumer
      processes, this is not the end of the world. However, if the
      process was a producer, the ring buffer will not allow a new
      producer process to attach to it. In this case, the ring buffer is
      just fooled and needs to be reset using the ringbuffer format.
    </para>

    <para>
      Complete reference documentation of the
      <command>ringbuffer</command> 
      can be found in the
      <link linkend="manpage.ringbuffer">ringbuffer</link> reference pages
    </para>

  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Data Transfer and Flow Control</title>

    <para>
      The last section just scratched the surface on the ring buffer and gave a
      functional overview of how to use it. In this section, we will discuss
      how it works in a bit more detail in hopes to remove some of its mystery.
      In what follows, we'll describe a single producer, single consumer ring
      buffer first and then generalize to a single producer multi-consumer ring
      buffer.
    </para>
    <para>
      Suppose we have a chunk of memory which is shareable between processes
      and within which we are going to use modulo addressing.  Using modulo
      addressing means that if we have a pointer sequentially accessing this
      memory, when the pointer would run off the end of this memory region
      instead it returns to the beginning.
    </para>
    <para>
      You can therefore think of this memory as an 'endless' ring of addresses.
      A <firstterm>ring buffer</firstterm>.
    </para>
    <para>
      For a ring buffer to be useful as a mechanism for exchanging data we need
      a bit more information.  Specifically, we need a <firstterm>put
        pointer</firstterm> and a <firstterm>get pointer</firstterm>.  As we
      will see we also need some concept of flow control.
    </para>
    <para>
      Here's how this all works.  Define the ring buffer as being empty if the
      put and get pointers are equal.  Define the ring buffer as full if
      advancing the put pointer one storage unit would make it equal to the get
      pointer (we don't want an ambiguity between full and empty ring buffers).
      A producer will ensure it has space in the ring buffer for whatever data
      it wants to put by calculating the modulo distance between the put and
      get pointers.  When space becomes available (producers wait if necessary
      for space), data are transferred to the ring buffer starting at the
      location indicated by the put pointer (using modulo addressing again).
      When the data are transferred, the put pointer is advanced to point to
      the location just following the message.
    </para>
    <para>
      Similarly, a consumer that wants to get data from the ring ensures there
      is enough data to get by waiting until the distance between the put and
      get pointers is at least the size of the data transfer it wants to
      perform.  Once there is sufficient data in the ring buffer it transfers
      the data out of the ring and, when the data have been read, updates the
      get pointer so that it points to the next unread unit of memory.
    </para>
    <para>
      This business of the produceer waiting for space to be available and the
      consumer waiting for data to be available is called flow control.
    </para>
    <para>
      In a data acquisition system, we usually want to have several consumers.
      This can be accomodated by having more than one get pointer.  This
      slightly complicates the flow control logic of the producer.  Now the
      producer must consider the free space to be the minimum distance between
      the the put pointer and all of the get pointers.
    </para>
    <para>
      The result of this is that ring buffers are a very low overhead mechanism to transfer
      data between processes in a single shared memory computer system.
      Messages can be atomically put without any requirement to negotiate
      locks.  Furthermore, since data are in shared memory, it's not necessary
      to transfer buffers to kernel space and then back out to application
      space.  For more information about ring buffers see <ulink
        url='http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Circular_buffer'>
        http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Circular_buffer </ulink> 
    </para>
    <para>
      Finally, the data transferred through the ring buffer is just
      a stream of bytes, in practice and in the NSCL Ring buffer Data
      Acquisition system, we send messages that have structure. The messages
      have a structure defined later in <xref linkend="chapter.ringformat"/>.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Proxy Rings, Ring Masters, and Network Transparency</title>
    <section>
      <title>Proxy Rings</title>
      <para>
        In a data data acquisition system we usually want several such computer
        systems to join the party.  Data taken in one system must be made
        visible in near real-time to analysis software in other computer
        systems.  This section describes the mechanism used by the NSCL Ring
        Buffer data acquisition system to accomplish this feat.
      </para>
      <para>
        Each system that runs the ring buffer data acquisition system
        has a simple server process called the <application>RingMaster</application>.
        We'll talk more about the RingMaster and its role in the next
        section.
      </para>
      <para>
        One role the ring master performs is to assist in hoisting
        data out of an local ring, sending it across the network to
        another system.  This is done through a mechanism called a
        <firstterm>proxy ring</firstterm> which makes the semantics
        of getting data from a remote system identical to the semantics
        of getting data from a local system.      
      </para>
      <para>
        If a process attempts to open a ring buffer whose URL does not
        specify <literal>localhost</literal> as the hostname, the ring buffer
        DAQ system contacts the RingMaster in the target host and collaborates
        with it to create a local ring and a network pipeline that
        ships data from the ring in the remote host to the local proxy ring.
        Only the first consumer goes through the gymnastics of creating a proxy
        ring and subsequent consumers simply connect to the proxy as an
        additional consumer. In this way, network traffic between rings and
        their proxies are aggregated.
      </para>
      <para>
        A proxy ring has the local name <literal>hostname.remote-ringname</literal>
        where <literal>hostname</literal> is the host in which the
        'real ring' is located and <literal>remote-ringname</literal>
        is the name of the real ring in <literal>hostname</literal>.
        Thus the proxy ring for <literal>tcp://spdaq42/fox</literal>
        will be <literal>tcp://localhost/spdaq42.fox</literal>.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>The RingMaster server</title>
      <para>
        All systems that run the Ring buffer data acquisition system
        also run a simple server called the <application>RingMaster</application>.
        The RingMaster performs the following functions:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Collaborates with remote clients to set up a pipeline
            to produce data into proxy rings as described in the
            previous section.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Allocate ring resources for local consumers.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Cleans up when local consumer exit or release their
            ring resources.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        The Ring buffer DAQ system has two types of clients.  Producers
        and consumers.  Recall that each ring can have at most one
        producer, and many consumers.
      </para>
      <para>
        The ring master keeps track of which local processes are attached
        to a ring and whether or not a process is the producer or
        a consumer (actually a consumer could be consuming data from several rings,
        or even be more than one consumer on one ring).
      </para>
      <para>
        When a client wants to obtain the put or a get pointer,
        it asks the ring master for one.  It does so by opening a
        TCP/IP connection to the ring master and sending it a pointer
        request message.  The ring master identifies the pointer
        it provides to the client.  The client is then required to hold
        the TCP/IP connection open.  If the TCP/IP connection closes,
        as it will normally  if a process exits, the RingMaster releases
        the pointer that was associated with that connection.
      </para>
      <para>
        In this way, ring buffers are immune to stalls that could occur
        if a pointer got orphaned.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Ring buffer utilities</title>
    <para>
      This section will give a brief overview of some of the ring buffer
      utilities.  Please refer to the remainder of this documentation
      for detailed descriptions and reference material for each utility.
      This list is only a selection of utilities.
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><application>ringbuffer</application></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This utility allows you to create, re-initialize, delete  and
            monitor the status of ringbuffers.  Normally you don't have to
            create ring buffers as producer frameworks will create them if they
            don't already exist. See the <link
              linkend="manpage.ringbuffer">man page</link> for more information.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><application>dumper</application></term>
        <listitem><para>
            Provides a simple textual formatted dump of the buffers.  If you
            want more advanced formatting, you can use the
            <application>tkdumper</application> application.  By contrast with
            <application>dumper</application>,
            <application>tkdumper</application> can be extended with plugins in
            such a way that it can provide a human readable formatted view of
            each event and the packets within the event. See <link linkend="ch.dumper">user documentation</link> and <link
              linkend="manpage.dumper">man page</link> for more information.
        </para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><application>eventlog</application></term>
        <listitem><para>
            Performs native mode event loggging.  In this mode, event file
            segments consists of streams of ring buffer items. See <link linkend="chap.eventlog">user documentation</link> and <link
              linkend="manpage.eventlog">man page</link> for more information.
        </para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><application>ringselector</application></term>
        <listitem><para>
            Provides a flexible ringbuffer consumer that pipes the ring items
            it gets to standard output.  This can be run over a pipe into your
            program or as the first stage of a pipeline that transforms data
            before providing it to an application. Unlike other processes, this
            will never introduce flow control and is suitable for sampling
            applications like SpecTcl. See <link
              linkend="chapter.ringselector">user documentation</link> and <link
              linkend="manpage.ringselector">man page</link> for more information.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><application>ringtostdout</application></term>
        <listitem><para>
            Accepts data from a ring and pipes it to stdout.  This is the server
            side of the pipeline between systems when you are setting up a proxy
            ring.  It can also be used as the first stage of a pipeline to
            process data from  a ring. See the <link
              linkend="manpage.ringtostdout">man page</link> for more information.
        </para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><application>ScalerDisplay</application></term>
        <listitem><para>
            Provides a display of scaler event data.  This application is highly
            configurable.  It can accept an arbitrary number of scalers and
            format any number of pages as tabs in a notebook.  Strip charts of
            selected scalers are also supported. See <link
              linkend="chapter.scalerdisplay">user documentation</link> and <link
              linkend="manpage.scalerdisplay">man page</link> for more information.
        </para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><application>stdintoring</application></term>
        <listitem><para>
            Accepts data on stdin and puts it in a ring buffer.  This is the
            client side of the data pipeline that sets up a proxy ring. See the <link
              linkend="manpage.stdintoring">man page</link> for more information.
        </para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>
</chapter>
<!-- /chapter -->

