<!-- chapter user-guide -->
<chapter>
    <title>ReadoutGUI &amp; ReadoutShell</title>
    <para>
        The <literal>ReadoutShell</literal> is a graphical user interface that
        servers as a front end for experiment control. The terms ReadoutShell
        and ReadoutGUI are typically used interchangeably, though
        ReadoutGUI properly refers to the packaged user interface and
        ReadoutShell properly refers to the program that launches the
        ReadoutGUI interface. The <literal>ReadoutGUI</literal> for NSCLDAQ-11 is
        significantly different than that of earlier versions.  The
        ReadoutShell for NSCLDAQ-11 has been built to better support the
        multi-data source/event builder environment that NSCLDAQ-11 provides.
    </para>
    <para>
        The remainder of this chapter describes:
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    The principles of operation of the ReadoutShell.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    The ReadoutShell's GUI (ReadoutGUI) and how to operate it.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    The way the event logger ties into the Readout GUI and
                    The directory structure the ReadoutShell maintains
                    to support an experiment.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Ways in which the ReadoutShell supports customization
                    of both its appearance and operation.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Reference material on the API provided by the ReadoutShell can be found in
      the <link linkend='rdogui_man'>3rdogui</link> man page section.      
    </para>
    <section>
        <title>Principles of operation</title>
        <para>
            This chapter describes the underlying principles of operation
            of the event builder.  Along the way terminology that will be used
            in the remainder of this chapter will be informally defined.
        </para>
        <para>
            The purpose of the ReadoutShell is to provide a graphical user interface
            that can control a set of readout programs or <firstterm>Data Sources</firstterm>.
            To do this, the ReadoutShell must know how to ask readout programs
            of various types to start, stop, pause and resume (if supported) runs.
            To do this it uses a set of <firstterm>Data Source Providers</firstterm>.
            You can think of a data source provider as a set of software that knows
            how to run a specific type of data source program.
        </para>
        <para>
            The ReadoutShell and Data source providers communicate via a
            well defined programmatic interface that is described in
            <link linkend="provider3_intro">3provider</link>.
        </para>
        <para>
            At the core of the ReadoutShell is a finite state automaton or
            <firstterm>State Machine</firstterm>.  The State machine defines
            a set of running modes or <firstterm>States</firstterm> the ReadoutShell
            can be in as well as the set of legal states to which the system
            can proceed via <firstterm>State Transitions</firstterm>.
            The ReadoutShell state machine provides a mechanism for other
            components of the ReadoutShell to register an interest in the transitions
            between states and to take appropriate action both prior to leaving
            a state and upon completing the transition to the new state.
            Functionality that is registered on a state machine is referred to
            as a <firstterm>bundle</firstterm>
        </para>
        <para>
            For example, event logging is implemented as a bundle.  As the
            state machine is transitioning from a halted state to an active state,
            the event log bundle starts up the event logger. When the state machine
            transitions either from the paused, or active states to the halted
            state, the bundle waits for logging to complete and then finalizes
            the run data by maintaining the correct filesystem/directory
            structure.
        </para>
        <para>
            We complete this section with a diagram of the state machine
            and a description of each state, what it means to be in that state,
            the legal transitions from that state and what it means to make
            those transitions.
        </para>
        <figure id='rdogui_statediagram'>
            <title id='rdogui_statediagram_title'>ReadoutShell's state diagram</title>
            <mediaobject>
               <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref='RunState.jpg' format='JPEG' />
                </imageobject>
               <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref='RunState.eps' format='EPS' />
               </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>
            As we will see in the discussion below, some of the transitions
            that go directly back to <literal>NotReady</literal> actually
            represent a transition through <literal>Halted</literal> followed by
            a transition to <literal>NotReady</literal>.  The diagram's transitions
            are abbreviated in order to reduce the complexity and provide the
            intent (that the 'stable' end state of the transition is
            <literal>NotReady</literal>).
        </para>
        <para>
            Let's look at each state from top to bottom.
        </para>
        <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><literal>NotReady</literal></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        This state means that none of the data sources are running
                        and therefore the system is not yet ready to be used.
                        In this state you can define the set of data sources
                        to use.  The <guibutton>Start</guibutton> button
                        causes a transition to the <literal>Starting</literal>
                        state.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><literal>Starting</literal></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        On making a transition to the <literal>Starting</literal>
                        state, the data source manager attempts to start all of the
                        data sources.  If any of the data sources fail to start,
                        a transition back to the <literal>NotReady</literal> state
                        is forced.  Once all data sources start successfully,
                        the data source manager forces a transition to the
                        <literal>Halted</literal> state.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><literal>Halted</literal></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        In the <literal>Halted</literal> state, the system is
                        ready for use.  The <guibutton>Begin</guibutton> button
                        can start a data taking run transitioning to the
                        <literal>Active</literal> state.  If a data source
                        fails, the system will transition back to the
                        <literal>NotReady</literal> state.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><literal>Active</literal></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        In this state, all data sources are actively taking data.
                        If a data source fails, the data source manager will
                        attempt to gracefully stop the run (transition to
                        <literal>Halted</literal>).  Regardless, eventually
                        a failing data source will result in the <literal>NotReady</literal>
                        state.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        If all data sources being used support paused runs, the
                        <guibutton>Pause</guibutton> button is available
                        and clicking it will result in a transition to the
                        <literal>Paused</literal> state.
                        The <guibutton>End</guibutton> button is always available
                        in this state and forces a transition to <literal>Halted</literal>,
                        cleanly ending the run.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><literal>Paused</literal></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        This state represents a temporary halt of data taking
                        that does not close event files.   The
                        state is only reachable if all event sources support
                        pausing a run. If not, the <guibutton>Pause</guibutton>
                        button is not shown so operators of the GUI cannot
                        force a transition to this state.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Once <literal>Paused</literal> clicking the
                        <guibutton>Resume</guibutton> button forces a transtion
                        back to the <literal>Active</literal> state while
                        clicking the <guibutton>End</guibutton> button forces
                        a transition to the <literal>Halted</literal> state (ending
                        the run).
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        If any data source fails during the <literal>Paused</literal>
                        state, the data source manager attempts to force a transition
                        to the <literal>Halted</literal> state prior to forcing a
                        transition to the <literal>NotReady</literal> state.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
                
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Operating the user interface</title>
        <para>
            Below is a screenshot of the graphical user interface presented by
            the ReadoutShell program.
        </para>
        <figure>
            <title>ReadoutShell's GUI</title>
            <mediaobject>
               <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref='readoutshell.jpg' format='JPEG' />
                </imageobject>
               <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref='readoutshell.eps' format='EPS' />
               </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>
            The GUI is divided into four vertically stripped segments. From
            top to bottom these segments are:
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    The <firstterm>Menu Bar</firstterm> which provides acces
                    to infrequenly used operations and commands.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    The <firstterm>Run management segment</firstterm>
                    which allows you to set up run
                    parameters and to manage the ReadoutShell's state machine
                    as far as you are supposed to be able to stimulate it.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    The <firstterm>Output Log window</firstterm> which provides
                    a scrolling text widget in which modules that make up the
                    RadoutShell can place textual messages.   In many cases
                    the messages are output in a log/severity format which just
                    means that messages have a timestamp and a severity and that the
                    severity affects the formatting of the messages.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    The <firstterm>Status Bar</firstterm> which provides a region
                    for modules that make up the ReadoutShell, and data providers
                    to display status information that will not scroll away.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <section>
            <title>The Menu bar</title>
            <para>
                The menu bar provides access to ReadoutShell commands
                that are not as frequently used as those that are presented
                by the Run Management segment described below.  In addtion
                to the fixed menus described in this section,
                <link linkend='customizing_readoutshell'
                      endterm='customizing_readoutshell_title' /> describes
                how your extensions to ReadoutShell can add more entries to the
                menus or create entirely new menus.
            </para>
            <formalpara>
                <title>The File menu</title>
                <para>
                    Provides access to file related commands.  The
                    specific operations provided are:
                    <variablelist>
                        <varlistentry>
                            <term><menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Load...</guimenuitem></menuchoice></term>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    This command prompts for a file which must be
                                    a Tcl/Tk script.  The script selected is then
                                    sourced into the ReadoutShell.  The source is
                                    done in global level context.
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </varlistentry>
                        <varlistentry>
                            <term><menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu>
                                <guimenuitem>Add Library..</guimenuitem></menuchoice></term>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    This command prompts for a directory.  The
                                    directory is then added to the path of
                                    directories that is searched for Tcl packages.
                                    This can be used, for example, to add a directory
                                    or set of directories that have data source
                                    provider packages to the search path making
                                    them known to the data source manager.
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </varlistentry>
                        <varlistentry>
                            <term><menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Log...</guimenuitem></menuchoice></term>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    Prompts for a file.  Once the file is selelcted,
                                    all output sent to the Output Log window is
                                    also logged to this file. Logging continues
                                    until either the <guimenuitem>Disable Log</guimenuitem>
                                    command is seleted, the program exits, or another
                                    log file is selected.
                                </para>
                                <para>
                                    If the selected log file already exists,
                                    it is opened for append, allowing a single file to
                                    easily log the output from more than one session.
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </varlistentry>
                        <varlistentry>
                            <term><menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Disable Log</guimenuitem></menuchoice></term>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    Once seleted, if logging has been established,
                                    the log file is closed.
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </varlistentry>
                        <varlistentry>
                            <term><menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Exit...</guimenuitem></menuchoice></term>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    After prompting for confirmation, exits the ReadoutShell.
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </varlistentry>
                    </variablelist>
                </para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>The Data Source menu</title>
                <para>
                    This menu provides operations that allow you to establishthe set of
                    data sources you will be using and well as to list data sources
                    and their parameterizations.
                    <variablelist>
                        <varlistentry>
                            <term><menuchoice><guimenu>Data Source</guimenu>
                                <guimenuitem>Add...</guimenuitem></menuchoice></term>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    Allows you to add a data source to the set of data
                                    sources being used by the Readout GUI.  This can only
                                    be done when the state is not <literal>Paused</literal>
                                    or <literal>Active</literal>.  This also forces all
                                    running data sources to stop and transitions the state
                                    to the <literal>Not Ready</literal> state.
                                </para>
                                <para>
                                    Prompting for a data source is a two step operation.
                                    First you will be prompted for the Data source Provider
                                    (data source type) you want to use.  The built
                                    in providers are <literal>SSHPipe</literal> (suitable
                                    for Readout programs that operate on the
                                    end of an ssh pipeline),
                                    <literal>S800</literal> which knows how to
                                    control the S800 data acquisition system, <literal>Delay</literal>
                                    (used for inserting delay between providers), and 
                                    <literal>RemoteGUI</literal> (for remote controlling a 
                                    ReadoutGUI).
                                </para>
                                <para>
                                    Data sources are parameterized instances
                                    of a data source provider.  For example, the
                                    <literal>SSHPipe</literal> data source needs
                                    to  know which host the data source runs in
                                    as well as the program to run on the end
                                    of the pipe.  Optionally it an accept command
                                    line parameters for the program.
                                </para>
                                <para>
                                    Once you have been prompted for the
                                    data source provider, you will be prompted
                                    for its parameterization.  The dialog used
                                    to prompt for the data source parameterization
                                    will appear differently depending on the
                                    provider you choose.
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </varlistentry>
                        <varlistentry>
                            <term><menuchoice><guimenu>Data Source</guimenu>
                                <guimenuitem>Delete...</guimenuitem></menuchoice></term>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    Presents a list of data sources and their
                                    parameterizations.  You can click on a
                                    data source to select it. Click
                                    <guibutton>Ok</guibutton> to delete the
                                    selected data source or <guibutton>Cancel</guibutton>
                                    to do nothing.
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </varlistentry>
                        <varlistentry>
                            <term><menuchoice><guimenu>DataSource</guimenu>
                                <guimenuitem>List</guimenuitem></menuchoice></term>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    Lists the set of data sources you have currently
                                    selected for use and their parameterizations.
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </varlistentry>
                    </variablelist>
                </para>
            </formalpara>
            <note>
                 <title>Note</title>
                 <para>
                     Data sources set up in the Data source menu are saved
                     and read back in when you next start the ReadoutShell,
                     this means that in general you only have to set up your
                     data sources once.
                 </para>
             </note>
            <formalpara>  <!-- used to get a title for these paragraphs -->
                <title> The Settings menu</title>
                <para>
                    The settings menu currently  an
                    <menuchoice><guimenu>Settings</guimenu><guimenuitem>Event Recording>></guimenuitem></menuchoice>
                    selection and a
                    <menuchoice><guimenu>Settings</guimenu><guimenuitem>Output Window..</guimenuitem></menuchoice>
                    selection.
                </para>
            </formalpara>
                <para>
                    The
                    <menuchoice><guimenu>Settings</guimenu><guimenuitem>Output Window..</guimenuitem></menuchoice>
                    selection allows you to configure the shape of the output
                    window, the number of lines of history information
                    retained and accessible through the vertical scroll-bar.
                    A checkbutton also allows you to turn on or off the display
                    of debugging output.
                </para>
                <para>
                    The
                    <menuchoice><guimenu>Settings</guimenu><guimenuitem>Event Recording>></guimenuitem></menuchoice>
                    allows you to configure parameters that control the way
                    events are recorded.
                    This allows you to set up a large number
                    configuration parameters for the event logging program.
                    The dialog this menu pops up is a bit complex and therefore
                    will be shown and described below.
                </para>
           
            <figure>
                <title>The Eventlog settings dialog</title>
                <mediaobject>
                   <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref='eventlogsettings.jpg' format='JPEG' />
                    </imageobject>
                   <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref='eventlogsettings.eps' format='EPS' />
                   </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Event Log Program</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            This item allows you to select the event logging
                            program.  This is normally used either to do
                            NSCLDAQ-8.x event logging via the compatibility
                            tools, or to select the 10.x event logger when
                            using the 11.x ReadoutShell with 10.x software.
                        </para>
                        <para>
                            The
                            <guibutton>Browse...</guibutton>
                            button alows you to graphically
                            select the event logger.  You must be sure the event
                            logger will produce event segment files with names
                            that are compatible with what is expected by the
                            ReadoutShell.  See the section
                            <link linkend='readoutshell_filestruct'
                                  endterm='readoutshell_filestruct_title' /> for
                            more information about this.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Data Source Ring URI</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Allows you to override the ring from which data are
                            logged.  Note that if you are using the event builder,
                            it will override this setting using the output
                            ring from the event builder instead of your selection
                            here.
                        </para>
                        <para>
                            If you click the <guibutton>Known Rings..</guibutton>
                            button, you can choose from a list of rings.  This
                            list will include all local rings and all rings remote
                            rings from which data has been accepted previously.
                            It is possible that the ring you want won't be
                            listed (if it is a remote ring from which data has
                            not been taken since the last reboot).  In that
                            case you can type in the ring specification which
                            is of the form
                            <literal>tcp://</literal><replaceable>host-name</replaceable><literal>/</literal><replaceable>ringname</replaceable>
                            Where <replaceable>host-name</replaceable> is the name
                            of the host on which the ring producer is located
                            and <replaceable>ringname</replaceable> is the name
                            of the ring in that host.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Use <option>--number-of-sources</option></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            This checkbutton causes the ReadoutGUI to use the
                            <option>--number-of-sources</option> option when
                            starting the event logger.  It can only be used with
                            the NSCLDAQ-11.x and later native event logger.
                        </para>
                        <para>
                            This option should be used if you are combining
                            the data from more than one event source using the
                            NSCLDAQ-11.x or later event builder.
                            See
                            <link linkend='manpage.eventlog'
                                  endterm='manpage.eventlog_title' /> for more
                            detailed information about this option.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Additional Sources</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            This option is related to the <literal>use --number-of-sources</literal>
                            checkbutton and only does something if that box is checked.
                            When <literal>use --number-of-sources</literal> is checked,
                            the ReadoutShell computes a
                            <firstterm>base source count</firstterm> from the
                            number of data sources it is controlling.  The
                            signed value of the <literal>Additional Sources</literal>
                            field is added to the base source count and used as
                            the value of the <option>--number-of-sources</option>
                            option when starting the event logger.
                            This value is the number of end run records the event
                            logger will expect to see to indicate all data in a
                            run has been received/recorded.
                        </para>
                        <para>
                            Usually <literal>0</literal> is the right value for
                            this control.  If, however you have data sources
                            which are not being managed by the ReadoutShell, you
                            may need to put a positive number in this box.
                            If you have data sources which are managed by the
                            ReadoutShell that don't produce end run records,
                            you may need to use a negative value here to adjust
                            the base source count downward.
                        </para>
                        <para>
                            The important thing is that the base source count
                            as modified by this value must be the number of active
                            sources that produce NSCL end run records at the
                            end of a data taking run.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Use GUI Run number</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            This checkbox determines if the ReadoutShell uses
                            the <option>--run</option> option when starting the
                            eventlog program.  When this option is used, its
                            value is the value in the ReadoutShell's run  number
                            control in the Run management segment of the GUI.
                            That value overrides anything eventlog might see in
                            the data stream and determines the run number field
                            of the filename in the event segments it generates.
                        </para>
                        <para>
                            This checkbutton should normally  not be checked.  It
                            should only be checked if all data sources are non-NSCL
                            data sources and none of them generate anything
                            like a begin run record that has a run number.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>The Run Management segment</title>
            <para>
                Below the ReadoutShell menubar are a set of controls that collectively
                make up the <firstterm>Run Management segment</firstterm>.  These
                are used to control data taking and the state of the system.
                Here is a description of the controls and what they do.
            </para>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Title</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            This entry control allows you to type in a title.
                            Titles can only be entered when the state of the
                            system is not <literal>Active</literal> or
                            <literal>Paused</literal>.  When the state is any of
                            those, the title entry is disabled.
                        </para>
                        <para>
                            When a run is started, the text in this title
                            field is passed to the data source provider for each
                            data source.  It is the responsibility of that provider
                            to know what to do.  NSCL data source providers
                            use this to set the title of the run in the data source.
                            For standard NSCL data sources this sets the title of
                            the begin run ring item record. For the S800, this
                            sets the title in the Begin run buffer.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Run Number</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            As with the titlwe field, this entry control is only
                            enabled when the state is not <literal>Active</literal>
                            or <literal>Paused</literal>. When you navigate
                            focus out of this control, the value of the control
                            is checked and, if it is not a positive integer
                            (<literal>0</literal> is legal), an error message pops up
                            and the field is restored to its prior value.
                        </para>
                        <para>
                            When a run is started, the run number is passed to
                            the data source providers for  all data sources.
                            For NSCL data sources this value is passed to the readout
                            program as the run number to place in state transition
                            records.
                        </para>
                        <para>
                            For the S800 data provider, the run number is passed
                            in and used by the S800 Data source to set the run
                            number in its state transition buffers.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Run Control cluster</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            The run control cluster is the set of two or
                            three buttons at the left side of the
                            Run Management segment.  The top button of this
                            cluster of buttons is always the <guibutton>Start</guibutton>
                            button.  It is enabled whenever the system is in the
                            <literal>NotReady</literal> state.
                        </para>
                        <para>
                            Clicking the <guibutton>Start</guibutton> button
                            transitions to the <literal>Starting</literal> state.
                            The data source manager then attempts to start
                            all of the data sources and, if successful, the
                            system transitions to the <literal>Halted</literal>
                            state.
                        </para>
                        <para>
                            The <guibutton>Begin/End</guibutton> button contains
                            a label and state that depends on the systsem state:
                        </para>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>The button is disabled when the system
                                    is in the <literal>NotReady</literal> or
                                    <literal>Starting</literal> state.
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>The button is enabled and labeled
                                    <literal>Begin</literal> when the state
                                    is <literal>Halted</literal>. In this state,
                                    when clicked, the system transitions to
                                    <literal>Active</literal> and all data sources
                                    are told to start taking data.
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>The button is enabled and labeled
                                    <literal>End</literal> when the state of the'
                                    system is <literal>Active</literal> or
                                    <literal>Paused</literal>.  When clicked in
                                    this state, the data sources are told to stop
                                    taking data (end the run), and the system
                                    transitions to the <literal>Halted</literal>
                                    state.
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                        <para>
                            If all data sources support pausing a run, a third
                            button appears in this cluster.  The third button
                            is the <guibutton>Pause/Resume</guibutton> button.
                        </para>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    This button is disabled when the system
                                    is not in the <literal>Active</literal>
                                    or <literal>Paused</literal> state.
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    This button is enabled and labeled
                                    <guibutton>Pause</guibutton> when the system
                                    is in the <literal>Active</literal> state.
                                    If clicked in that state, the system transitions
                                    to the <literal>Paused</literal> state and
                                    all data sources are instructed to pause data
                                    taking but keep the run alive.
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    This button is enabled and labeled
                                    <guibutton>Resume</guibutton>. Clicking
                                    this button transition to the <literal>Active</literal>
                                    state after instructing all data sources
                                    to resume data taking in their paused run.
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><guibutton>Record</guibutton></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            This is located below the Run control cluster.
                            It is enabled only when the state is not
                            <literal>Active</literal> or <literal>Paused</literal>
                            when checked, the next begin run will also initiate
                            the event logger as configured by the
                            <menuchoice><guimenu>Settings</guimenu><guimenuitem>Event Recording...</guimenuitem></menuchoice>
                            menu item.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Active Run Time</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            This is located to the right of the <guibutton>Start</guibutton>
                            button.  This represents the elapsed time of the
                            current or most recent run.  The timer is cleared
                            when a run begins, pauses when a run is paused
                            and runs when in the <literal>Active</literal> state.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Timed Run Controls</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            This set of controls is located to the right
                            of the <guibutton>Begin</guibutton> and
                            <guibutton>Pause</guibutton> (if visible) buttons.
                            The controls consist of two segments:
                        </para>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    A <literal>Timed Run</literal> checkbutton
                                    which, when checked automatically ends
                                    a run when the Active run time counter
                                    reaches the selected length
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    A set of drop downs that allow you to
                                    select the length of time a run will
                                    be active if timed.
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>The Output Log window</title>
            <para>
                The output log window provides a scrolling window for messages
                from components of the ReadoutShell and data sources.
                Must but not all messages will include a timestamp as well
                as a logging type.  The log type may also carry some visual form
                of emphasis.
            </para>
            <para>
                Note that when event logging is active, the background of ths
                window is Spartan Green, otherwise it is grey.
            </para>
            <para>
                Unless otherwise noted below, log entries are in black text
                on the current background.
                The log types are currently:
            </para>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><literal>debug</literal></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            The <literal>debug</literal> log level is intended
                            to provide debugging/tracing information that shows
                            programmers the internal operation of components of
                            the ReadoutShell.
                            By default these log entries are not displayed.
                            See, however
                            <link linkend='rdogui3_ui_OutputWindow'
                                endterm='rdogui3_ui_OutputWindow_title' />  for
                            information on how to make these visible.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><literal>log</literal></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Log entries at the <literal>log</literal> level
                            log a significant event that represents the normal
                            operation of the program.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><literal>output</literal></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            <literal>output</literal> log entries capture
                            output from a program that is being run under the
                            control of the ReadoutShell (usually a data source).
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><literal>warning</literal></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            <literal>warning</literal> log entries are intended
                            to warn you of an unusual condition.  They are
                            displayed in magenta text on the current background.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><literal>error</literal></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            <literal>error</literal> log entries are intended
                            to inform you of a problem.  A typical cause of an
                            error is the unexpected exit of a data source.
                            Error log messagesa are displayed in red on a white
                            background.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
            <para>
                The log types and their visual representations can be controlled
                programmatically. See
                <link linkend='rdogui3_ui_OutputWindow'
                      endterm='rdogui3_ui_OutputWindow_title' /> for information
                that describes how to locate the output window widget
                and the interfaces it provides.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>The Status Bar</title>
            <para>
                At the very bottom of the ReadoutShell GUI is the status bar.
                This is used by components of the ReadoutShell and its
                extensions to provide status information about their operation
                that should not scroll out of the visible part of the Output
                Window.  Currently the only use of the status bar by the
                core ReadoutShell components is to display the event recording
                status of active runs.
            </para>
        </section>
        
    </section>
    <section id='readoutshell_filestruct'>
        <title id='readoutshell_filestruct_title'>The event logger and ReadoutShell</title>
        <para>
            The Readout GUI works with the event logger to maintain
            a directory structure of event files and associated data.
            You can associate an arbitrary set of files and directory subtrees
            with each run.  Through heavy use of symbolic links, the
            Readout GUI provides you with two views of your data.
        </para>
        <formalpara>
            <title>Events view</title>
            <para>
                The events view presents all of the event files in a single
                directory.  This view allows you to sequentially analyze
                several runs without needing to move around in the directory
                hierarchy.
            </para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara>
            <title>Runs view</title>
            <para>
                This view collects all of the data associated with each run
                into a single directory.
            </para>
        </formalpara>
        <para>
            The top of the directory subtree that is managed by Readout Gui is
            determined by a symbolic link; <filename>~/stagearea</filename>.
            <footnote>
                <para>
                    Environment variables can override this link however and are
                    useful in the event you are using a single account to do
                    multiple tests for which you want to segregate the data.
                </para>
            </footnote>
            This must be created by you when you set the account up for data taking
            and should point to the event area that you were assigned.
        </para>
        <para>
            When Readout GUI runs the first time it will create the directory
            structure it need underneath the directory pointed to by
            <filename>~/stagearea</filename>.
        </para>
        <para>
            The directory tree created looks like this:
        </para>
        <figure>
            <title>Readout GUI Directory tree</title>
            <literallayout><![CDATA[
stagearea +
          +----> experiment+
          |                +---> current
          |                +---> run1
          |                +---> run2
          ...             ...
          +----> complete
          +----> current
            ]]>
            </literallayout>
        </figure>
        <para>
            Let's start with the <filename>~/stagearea/current</filename> directory.
            The Readout GUI arranges for the event file set currently being
            accumulated to be written in this directory.  Event files have the name
            <literal>run-nnnn-ss.evt</literal> where <literal>nnnn</literal> is a
            zero filled run number (e.g. <literal>0001</literal>), and
            <literal>ss</literal> is a zero filled event segment.
        </para>
        <para>
            The event data from each run are segmented into files that are no
            more than 2GBytes long.  The segments number from 00.  Segmenting
            runs into file that are no larger than 2Gbytes avoids problems
            with file size limitations on some types of file systems.
        </para>
        <para>
            The <filename>~/stagearea/experiment</filename> subdirectory tree
            provides the run view of the data.  Within that directory are
            subdirectories for each recorded run.  At the end of a run,
            the Readout GUI moves the event data files from the
            <filename>~/stagearea/current</filename> directory into the
            associated run directory.  The data in
            <filename>~stagearea/experiment/current</filename> is copied into
            the run directory as well.  Files or directories pointed to by
            symoblic links in the <filename>experiment/current</filename> subtree
            are copied rather than the links themselves.
        </para>
        <para>
            Finally, the <filename>complete</filename> directory provides the
            events view of the experiment.  At the end of a run, after the
            event file segments copied to <filename>~stagearea/experiment/runn</filename>,
            a symbolic link to each event file segment is created here.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section id='customizing_readoutshell'>
        <title id='customizing_readoutshell_title'>Customizing the ReadoutShell</title>
        <para>
            The ReadoutShell can be customized in several ways.
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Environment variables can affect the operation of
                        the ReadoutShell.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        The <filename>ReadoutCallouts.tcl</filename> script
                        can provide additional code that executes at times
                        during state machine transitions.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        The <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Load...</guimenuitem></menuchoice>
                        menu command can load an arbitrary Tcl script which can
                        register itself with the run state machine.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        The <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Add Library...</guimenuitem></menuchoice>
                        menu command can add library directories that are searched
                        for packages that supply additional data source providers.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <para>
            The remainder of this section describes these customization paths.
            Each subsection points to appropriate reference information.
        </para>
        <section>
            <title>Environment variables</title>
            <para>
                This section describes sets of related environment variables
                that can affect the way the ReadoutShell operates.
            </para>
            <table>
                <title>Event logger environment variables</title>
                <tgroup cols='3' align='left' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                    <thead>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Variable Name</entry>
                            <entry>Default Value</entry>
                            <entry>Meaning</entry>
                        </row>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry>EVENTLOGGER</entry>
                            <entry>$DAQROOT$/bin/eventlog</entry>
                            <entry>Selects the program that will be used to log events.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>EVENTLOGGER_RING</entry>
                            <entry>tcp://localhost/$::tcl_platform(user)</entry>
                            <entry>Selects the ring from which the event
                                   logger logs data. Note that ::tcl_platform(user)
                                   is a Tcl variable that is always defined to
                                   be the  name of the logged in user.
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>EVENTLOGGER_NSRCSFLAGS_SUPPORTED</entry>
                            <entry>true</entry>
                            <entry>If true the event logger will be started with the
                                <option>--number-of-sources</option>
                                option provided as
                                described earlier. If false, this flag will be
                                omitted.  The variable accepts any valid Tcl
                                boolean value (e.g. true, false, on, off, 1, 0).
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>EVENTLOGGER_UNCONTROLLED_SOURCE_COUNT</entry>
                            <entry>0</entry>
                            <entry>Integer value added to the base source count
                                to provide the value for
                                <option>--number-of-sources</option>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>EVENTLOGGER_USE_GUI_RUNNUM</entry>
                            <entry>0</entry>
                            <entry>If Tcl boolean true, the run number for the
                                current run will be provided to the eventlog
                                program via the <option>--run</option> flag
                                to determine the name of the event files.
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>EVENTLOGGER_USE_CHECKSUM_FLAG</entry>
                            <entry>1</entry>
                            <entry>If Tcl boolean true, an sha512 hash of 
                                all logged data will be computed by 
                                passing the <option>--checksum</option> flag
                                to the program.
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
            <para>
                Note that settings made using the
                <menuchoice><guimenu>Settings</guimenu><guimenuitem>Event Recording...</guimenuitem></menuchoice>
                override environment variables.  This includes settings that have
                been saved from prior runs of the program.
            </para>
            <para>
                The table below describes the settings used to control where
                data is saved.
            </para>
            <table>
                <title>Experiment file systems environment variables</title>
                <tgroup cols='3' align='left' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                    <thead>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Variable Name</entry>
                            <entry>Default Value</entry>
                            <entry>Meaning</entry>
                        </row>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry>EVENTS</entry>
                            <entry>~/stagearea</entry>
                            <entry>The root of the directory tree that
                            ReadoutGUI will use to manage the event and related
                            data.
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
            <note>
                <title>NOTE - difference from prior versions</title>
                <para>
                    In the 10.x and prior versions it was possible to separate
                    where the experiment view lived from where the event view
                    lived by specifying the <literal>EXPDIR</literal> environment
                    variable.   This variable is now ignored and that the
                    <filename>experiment</filename> directory will always live in the
                    <filename>stagearea</filename> directory tree.
                </para>
            </note>
            <para>
                SSHPipe clients also have default parameterizations.  These
                are based on the environment variables that were used by the
                10.x readout shell.  Reliance on these environment variables
                is not recommended, as they only populate the sshPIPE parameter
                prompter and because the point of this software is to
                manage multiple data sources rather so the concept of
                default data source parameters becomes a bit meaningless.
            </para>
            <para>
                The table below shows the environment variables that can populate
                the SSHPipe settings prompter:
            </para>
            <table>
                <title>SSHPipe prompter environment variables</title>
                <tgroup cols='3' align='left' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                    <thead>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Variable Name</entry>
                            <entry>Default Value</entry>
                            <entry>Meaning</entry>
                        </row>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry>DAQHOST</entry>
                            <entry>localhost</entry>
                            <entry>Host in which the readout program runs</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>RDOFILE</entry>
                            <entry><emphasis>undefined</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>The path to the program to run.
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
            <para>
                One last word.  In the past, ReadoutShell has failed to run
                properly because users have defined the environment variable
                <literal>TCLLIBPATH</literal> to include Tcl package directories
                from an older version of NSCLDAQ.  In the 11.x version of the
                program, if <literal>TCLLIBPATH</literal> is defined the program
                will exit with an error message unless you additionally define
                <literal>TCLLIPATH_OK</literal> which indicates that you are
                sure your <literal>TCLLIBPATH</literal> definition doesn not
                include any NSCLDAQ directories.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>ReadoutCallouts.tcl</title>
            <para>
                As with the 10.x and earlier ReadoutShells, the 11.0 program
                looks for a <filename>ReadoutCallouts.tcl</filename> file which,
                if found is sourced as the program is initialized.  This script
                can contain anything, however it's main purpose is to define one
                or more of a set of <command>proc</command>s that can be called
                by the ReadoutShell at specific times during the program's execution.
            </para>
            <para>
                The ReadoutShell looks for the <filename>ReadoutCallouts.tcl</filename>
<<<<<<< HEAD
                file in the following directories.  Only the first one is
                sourced in.  Sourcing is done at the global level.
            </para>
            <itemizedlist>
=======
                file in the following three locations.  Any ReadoutCallouts.tcl script
                found is sourced in at the global level. The search order (and
                thereby execution order) is:
            </para>
            <orderedlist>
>>>>>>> master
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <filename>~</filename> your home directory.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <filename>~/stagearea/experiment/current</filename> The
                        location the metadata associated with the current run is
                        stored.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <filename>.</filename> the current working directory.
                        at the time ReadoutShell was first started.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
<<<<<<< HEAD
            </itemizedlist>
=======
            </orderedlist>
>>>>>>> master
            <para>
                If ReadoutCallouts or any other script sourced into
                ReadoutShell provides them the following <command>proc</command>s
                are called.
            </para>
            <note>
                <title>NOTE</title>
                <para>
<<<<<<< HEAD
                    Two additional callouts not avaialble in <filename>ReadoutCallouts.tcl</filename>
=======
                    Two additional callouts not available in <filename>ReadoutCallouts.tcl</filename>
>>>>>>> master
                    scripts for NSCLDAQ-10.x and earlier have been added.
                </para>
            </note>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><command>OnBegin</command></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            This command is invoked when the <literal>Halted</literal>
                            state is left for the <literal>Active</literal> state.
                            The command is passed the number of the run that is
                            about to be started.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><command>OnEnd</command></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            This command is invoked when the <literal>Halted</literal>
                            state is being entered from either the
                            <literal>Active</literal> or <literal>Paused</literal>
                            states.  As with <command>OnBegin</command> the run
                            number of the run being ended is passed to the command.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><command>OnPause</command></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Called when the <literal>Paused</literal> state is
                            entered.  The run number of the current run is passed
                            in.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><command>OnResume</command></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Called when the <literal>Paused</literal> state
                            is left for <literal>Active</literal>. Again the
                            current run number is passed to the command.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><command>OnStart</command></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Called wen the <literal>Halted</literal> state
                            is entered from the <literal>Starting</literal> state
                            indicating that all event sources have started
                            without errors.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><command>OnFail</command></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Called when <literal>NotReady</literal> is
                            entered from any state other than
                            <literal>NotReady</literal>.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
            <para>
                Note that all procs described above are called at the global
                level (<command>uplevel #0</command>).
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Integrating Tcl scripts</title>
            <para>
                Besides automatically sourcing the <filename>ReadoutCallouts.tcl</filename>
                script described in the previous section, the ReadoutShell's
                <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Load...</guimenuitem></menuchoice>
                allows you to choose a Tcl/Tk script and source it at the
                global level at any time.
                The script you source can define any of the <command>proc</command>s
                described inthe previous section.  It can also invoke API
                <command>proc</command>s from the packages described in
                <link linkend='readoutshell_api_packages'
                      endterm='readoutshell_api_packages_title' />.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Libraries and Data source providers</title>
            <para>
                The <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Library...</guimenuitem></menuchoice>
                menu command allows you to choose a directory to be added to your
                library path.  One of the main reasons to do this is to add
                a custom data source provider.  This section describes in
                general terms how to create data source providers.  See
                <link linkend='provider3_intro'
                      endterm='provider3_intro_title' />
                for reference information on data source providers.
            </para>
            <para>
                Data source providers can be thought of as a class whose instances
                manage data sources.  In order to create a data source provider
                you must:
            </para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Create a provider package that encapsulates the
                    provider's interface into a Tcl <command>namespace</command>.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Optionally create a prompter package that encapsulates
                    provides a custom GUI prompter for the parameterization
                    of the data sources your data source provider manages.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>
                A data source provider has a name which we will refer to as
                <emphasis>providername</emphasis> in this chapter.  The provider
                must provide a Tcl package.  The name of that package must
                be <emphasis>providername</emphasis><literal>_Provider</literal>.
                Furthermore it must define a namespace
                <literal>::</literal><emphasis>providername</emphasis>.
                If these conditions are met, and the provider's package is in the
                Tcl library search path, the ReadoutShell's
                <menuchoice><guimenu>Data Source</guimenu><guimenuitem>Add...</guimenuitem></menuchoice>
                will list the <emphasis>providername</emphasis> as one of the
                providers available to add a data source
            </para>
            <para>
                Data sources have parameterizations.  It is differences in their
                parameterizations that typically distinguish between the data
                sources a provider manages.  Data sources describe their
                the form of their parameterizations via their
                <emphasis>providername</emphasis><literal>::parameters</literal>
                <command>proc</command>.   The <literal>parameters</literal>
                proc is described in
                <link linkend='provider3_parameters' endterm='provider3_parameters_title' />
            </para>
            <para>
                If the data source provider does not provide a parameter prompeter,
                the ReadoutShell will construct a default simple prompter from
                the information returned by the data sourcde provider's
                <literal>parameters</literal> proc.   This prompter will just
                be a bunch of verbose names and text entries for each name.
            </para>
            <para>
                If this prompter is too simplistic, it is possible for a
                data source provider to also define a prompter. A prompter is
                provide by providing a package named
                <emphasis>providername</emphasis><literal>_Prompter</literal>
                which defines the proc
                <literal>::</literal><emphasis>providername</emphasis><literal>::promptParameters</literal>.
                This proc is called by the ReadoutShell with no parameters and is
                expected to return the either the parameterization dict
                (see <link linkend='provider3_start' endterm='provider3_start_title' />)
                for information about this dict.  If the user declines to
                provide parameters (e.g. cancels the dialog prompter's dialog),
                the prompter should return an empty string.
            </para>
            <para>
                The parameterization of a data source, along with a data
                source id are passed to the
                <literal>::</literal><emphasis>providername</emphasis><literal>::start</literal>
                proc to start a data source.  The source id is a unique value
                that is generated by the ReadoutShell and used to refer to
                individual data sources.  The data source id is globally unique
                (not just unique to the provider). For more information
                abut starig data sources see:
                <link linkend='provider3_start' endterm='provider3_start_title' />.
            </para>
            <para>
                Not all data sources are created equal.  Thus a data source
                must provide a proc named
                <literal>::</literal><emphasis>providername</emphasis><literal>::capabilities</literal>
                that returns a dict that descsribes the capabilities of the
                data sources it manages.  For example, if a data source is not
                capable of pausing an active run its <literal>capabilities</literal>
                proc will report that in the dict it returns.
                For more information see:
                <link linkend='provider3_capabilities' endterm='provider3_capabilities_title' />
            </para>
            <para>
                Data sources must also provide a
                <literal>::</literal><emphasis>providername</emphasis><literal>::check</literal>
                proc.  The <literal>check</literal> proc is passed the data source
                id and is expected to return a boolean that is true if the
                data source is still alive or false if the data source is
                no longer alive.  The data source provider can expect the
                ReadoutShell to periodically poll its <literal>check</literal>
                proc so that it is able to report to the user an unexpected
                exit of a data source.
                The <literal>check</literal> proc is described more completely in
                <link linkend='provider3_check' endterm='provider3_check_title' />.
            </para>
            <para>
                Data source providers must know how to end a data source.  This
                mechanism is exposed to the ReadoutShell via a proc named:
                <literal>::</literal><emphasis>providername</emphasis><literal>::stop</literal>.
                This proc is passed the source id of the source to stop.
                For more information see:
                <link linkend='provider3_stop' endterm='provider3_stop_title' />.
            </para>
            <para>
                Finally, providers must be able to actually control their data
                sources.  This implies at a minimum providing
                <literal>::</literal><replaceable>providername</replaceable><literal>::begin</literal>
                to start a run and
                <literal>::</literal><replaceable>providername</replaceable><literal>::end</literal>
                to end a run.
                In addition, if the provider's capabilities include the ability
                to pause and resume an active run,
                <literal>::</literal><replaceable>providername</replaceable><literal>::pause</literal>
                and
                <literal>::</literal><replaceable>providername</replaceable><literal>::resume</literal>
                must also be supplied.
            </para>

            <para>
              The data source manager is capable of sending on-demand
              initialization to its registered data sources. It is thus required
              that each provider implements a proc named:
              <literal>::</literal><replaceable>providername</replaceable><literal>::init</literal>
              to handle on-demand initialization procedures. It is particularly
              useful for doing things like loading firmware.

            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Using the ReadoutGUI in your own container script</title>
            <para>
                The ReadoutShell is a very small script.  It simply creates
                an instance of a <literal>ReadoutGui</literal> object after
                getting the package paths set up properly.  This allows you
                to customize the way the Readout GUI is produced, not only via
                <filename>ReadoutCallouts.tcl</filename> scripts and
                State maching callback bundles, but by writing your own
                container script.
            </para>
            <para>
                If you are going to do this you'll certainly need to know
                about
                <link linkend='readoutshell_api_packages' endterm='readoutshell_api_packages_title' />
                and their contents so that you can effectively customize the
                behavior and appearance of the resulting GUI.
            </para>
            <para>
                Assuming the environment variable <literal>DAQROOT</literal>
                is defined and points to the top directory of the DAQ installation
                The example below shows a minimal ReadoutGUI startup script
                with  comments that show where to include customizations.
            </para>
            <example>
                <title>Custom ReadoutGUI startup script</title>
                <programlisting>

set TclLibs [file join $::env(DAQROOT) TclLibs]    <co id='custom_readoutgui_pkgdir' />
lappend auto_path $TclLibs

package require ReadoutGui
ReadoutGuiApp  r                                  <co id='custom_readoutgui_instance' />

                                                   <co id='custom_readoutgui_extend' />
                </programlisting>
            </example>
            <calloutlist>
                <callout arearefs='custom_readoutgui_pkgdir'>
                    <para>
                        This line and the next add the NSCLDAQ Tcl library
                        directory tree to the search path used by
                        <command>package require</command>.
                    </para>
                </callout>
                <callout arearefs='custom_readoutgui_instance'>
                    <para>
                        The previous line incorporates the <literal>ReadoutGui</literal>
                        package.  This package includes the entire Readout GUI
                        graphical user interface object set and also defines the
                        <classname>ReadoutGuiApp</classname> which drives the
                        Readout Graphical user interface.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        The line itself creates an instance of the class named
                        <varname>r</varname>.  Creating an <classname>ReadoutGuiApp</classname>
                        object creates the user interface and initializes it.
                        Initialization includes locating the
                        <filename>ReadoutCallouts.tcl</filename> script and
                        sourcing it.
                    </para>
                </callout>
                <callout arearefs='custom_readoutgui_extend'>
                    <para>
                        Once the <classname>ReadoutGuiApp</classname> application
                        object has been created additional customizations
                        can be done here.  These customizations include
                        invoking procs and methods from the various
                        <link linkend='readoutshell_api_packages'
                              endterm='readoutshell_api_packages_title' /> which
                        might alter the appearance or the behavior of the application.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Similarly, data source providers and additional
                        run state machine callback bundles can be registered
                        at this time.
                    </para>
                </callout>
            </calloutlist>
        </section>
        <section id='readoutshell_api_packages'>
            <title id='readoutshell_api_packages_title'>ReadoutGUI API packages</title>
            <para>
                This section will describe in general terms the packages that
                make up the ReadoutGui's application programming interface.
                pointers to reference material will be provided as well. 
            </para>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><literal>bells</literal></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            This package provides the <classname>bells</classname>
                            class.  This can be used to ring alarm bells in accordance with
                            some pattern.
                        </para>
                        <para>
                            See
                            <link linkend='rdogui3_bells' endterm='rdogui3_bells_title' />
                            for reference information.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><literal>Configuration</literal></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Provides a manager for configuration data.  This
                            package allows you to define configuration variables
                            and their defaults.  It also supports overidding
                            default values with environment variables.
                            Normally this package is used in conjunction with the
                            <literal>StateManager</literal> package to save
                            and restore the state of configuration parameters
                            to the configuration file.
                        </para>
                        <para>
                            See
                            <link linkend='rdogui3_configuration'
                                  endterm='rdogui3_configuration_title' />
                            for reference information.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><literal>DAQParameters</literal></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Provides access to parameters that affect data taking.
                            This package provides both query and modify access.
                            It uses the <literal>Configuration</literal> package
                            above.
                        </para>
                        <para>
                            See
                            <link linkend='rdogui3_daqparameters'
                                  endterm='rdogui3_daqparameters_title' />
                            for reference information.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><literal>DataSourceManager</literal></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            This package manages the data source providers
                            and data sources.  You need to interact with this
                            package if you want to create data sources
                            yourself (e.g. to create an exportable pre-packaged ReadoutGUI
                            for a specific setup).
                        </para>
                        <para>
                            See
                            <link linkend='rdogui3_DataSourceManager'
                                  endterm='rdogui3_DataSourceManager_title' />
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><literal>DataSourceUI</literal></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            This package provides the user interface
                            elements that prompt for data source parameters.
                            It provides at least one useful class
                            <classname>DialogWrapper</classname> which
                            can be  used to build custom prompters for
                            data source providers.
                        </para>
                        <para>
                            See
                            <link linkend='rdogui3_DatasourceUI'
                                  endterm='rdogui3_DatasourceUI_title' />
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><literal>Diagnostics</literal></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Provides simple error/warning/info dialogs.
                            See:
                            <link linkend='rdogui3_diagnostics'
                                  endterm='rdogui3_diagnostics_title' />
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><literal>ExpFileSystemConfig</literal></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Provides read/write access to configuration parameters
                            that determine where event data and related meta-data
                            are stored.
                            See:
                            <link linkend='rdogui3_expfilesystemconfig'
                                  endterm='rdogui3_expfilesystemconfig_title'
                                  />
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><literal>ReadoutGUI</literal></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Provides the readout GUI application class which
                            strings everything together. See
                            <link
                                  linkend='rdogui3_readoutgui'
                                  endterm='rdogui3_readoutgui_title' />
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><literal>ReadoutGUIPanel</literal></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Provides a group of API elements that allow you
                            to modify the user interface presented by the
                            <classname>ReadoutGuiApp</classname> application
                            object.
                            See:
                            <link linkend='rdogui3_readoutguipanel'
                                  endterm='rdogui3_readoutguipanel_title' />
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><literal>RunstateMachine</literal></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Implements the run state machine.  This also
                            provides the mechanism to register custom
                            callback bundles.
                            See:
                            <link linkend='rdogui3_runstatemachine'
                                  endterm='rdogui3_runstatemachine_title' />
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><literal>StateManager</literal></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Provides a package that supports simple Tcl
                            configuration files.  A simple Tcl configuration file
                            is a script with a bunch  of <command>set</command>
                            commands that define configuration variables.
                            The package allows you define variables that
                            are exported/imported from these files and
                            getters and setters for those variables.
                        </para>
                        <para>
                            See
                            <link linkend='rdogui3_statemanager'
                                  endterm='rdogui3_statemanager_title' />
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><literal>ui</literal></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Provides access to all elements of the user interface.
                            Before using this package, see if you needs are
                            met by the <literal>ReadoutGUIPanel</literal> package
                            since that tends to be easier to use.
                        </para>
                        <para>
                            See
                            <link linkend="rdogui3_ui" endterm='rdogui3_ui_title' />
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Remote control package</title>
      <para>
        When doing event building, it can be useful to have a ReadoutGUI for
        each data source and then another ReadoutGUI that controls them all.
        Doing this allows data sources to be worked on independently when
        it is not necessary to run all of them together to build events.
        The remote control packages for the ReadoutGUI support this
        mode of operation.
      </para>
      <para>
        If you choose to use this approach you must enable the ReadoutGUIs
        that will be slaved to the master control panel to:
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem><para>
              Run a remote control server component that allows the master
              GUI to tell it what to do.
          </para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>
              Run a remote console monitor component that allows the master
              GUI to relay output that goes to the slave output window to
              the master's output window.
          </para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
      <para>
        This is done by adding the following two lines to the slave
        GUI's <filename>ReadoutCallouts.tcl</filename> file:
      </para>
      <informalexample>
        <programlisting>
          package require ReadoutGuiRemoteControl   <co id='remote_control_package' />

          RemoteControlClient::initalize <co id='remote_control_initialize' />
        </programlisting>
      </informalexample>
      <calloutlist>
        <callout arearefs='remote_control_package'>
          <para>
            The remote control software is an optional component.
            This line incorporates that component into the ReadoutGUI
          </para>
        </callout>
        <callout arearefs='remote_control_initialize'>
          <para>
            An instance of the ReadoutGUIRemoteControl class and OutputClient
            are instantiated, thus providing the required capabilities for run
            control and output forwarding.  Furthermore, the
            <command>end</command> proc is renamed to
            <command>local_end</command> and a new <command>end</command> proc
            is created that will propagate an end run request to the master
            ReadoutGUI. This forwarding of the end run may be important if the
            enslaved GUI runs a filter in conjunction with the Actions package.
          </para>
        </callout>
      </calloutlist>
      <para>
        To use a slave UI, you must run a readout shell and add data sources
        with the RemoteGUI data source provider for each slave you want your master
        to control.  You will need to know which system is running the slave GUI
        and under which user name it is running. Furthermore, the system to be
        enslaved must have already been started (i.e. state = HALTED) in order
        for the master ReadoutGUI to enslave it.  
      </para>
      <para>
        At this time you can only have a single master control panel control
        any single slave control panel.  This restriction might be lifted in the
        future.
      </para>
    </section>

  </chapter>
<!-- /chapter -->
