<!-- chapter device-support -->
<chapter>
  <title>
    Mesytec MSCF-16 Controls 
  </title>

  <section>
    <title>Overview</title>

    <para>
      The Mesytec MSCF-16 is a 16-channel shaping amplifier with CFD.
      The device can be remotely controlled via either USB or Mesytec's RC-bus.
      A GUI called MCFD16Control is provided as a part of NSCLDAQ to control the
      device through the USB protocol only. 
      A key feature is the ability to
      generate a tcl script capable of configuring the device with the same
      settings displayed in the GUI.
    </para>

    <para>
      The parameters that the GUI provides control over are the threshold,
      gain, pole zero, shaping time, configuration mode, remote control mode,
      and also monitor channel.  All of these 
      can be set individually or commonly depending on the mode setting selected
      in the GUI. The interface reflects whether or not the device is being
      configured in either of these modes and prevents the setting of individual
      settings while in common mode.
    </para>

    <para>
      Finally, the control provided over the MSCF-16 through the GUI is made
      available through low-level drivers that can be used in any tclsh. The
      user can incorporate calls to these drivers in any script they want and
      can build input files to load into the GUI if desired.  In the same
      manner, if the user is in need of control of the device through the
      RC-bus, there is primitive support for communicating with a device through
      a digitizer in the MxDC family in VMUSBReadout. The user can then make the
      low level calls through the MXDCRCProxy snit::type.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Synchronization Paradigm</title>
    <para>
      It is worth pointing out that the GUI is much more tightly coupled to the 
      device than the MCFD16Control
      gui. It seeks to maintain good synchronization between the device and the
      gui at all times. What this means is that manipulating any of the widgets
      will cause the device to be manipulated. There is a short delay provided
      between the time the widget was changed and when the device is actually
      communicated with. This allows the user to make a number of changes to the
      same widget before any communication is attempted. The idea is that the
      user can double-click on a button or even hold down the increment on the
      spinbox without interruption. Once communication is attempted, the user is
      prevented from making changes until the the process is completed. 
    </para>

    <para>
      There is a targeted effort to provide the user with feedback about
      what is happening at any given moment. For that reason, a status message is
      updated at the bottom of the GUI to provide feedback.   
    </para>

  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Starting the GUI for USB communication</title>

    <para>
      To properly communicate over the USB protocol, the user should follow the
      the subsequent procedure. Before beginning, know that the device is
      particularly slow to respond over the USB protocol and so it is common for
      some bit of lag to exist when committing new parameters to the device.
    </para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Locate the name of the serial file that represents the MSCF-16 device.
          The serial file should be located in /dev with a name that begins with
          "ttyUSB". The number that forms the end of this file name is
          representative of the order in which the devices were plugged into the
          host computer. The number is therefore not unique and should be
          checked whenever the device is plugged in anew. Furthermore, ensure
          that this file is both readable and writable to your account. The
          spdaqs in the NSCL are configured to enforce these permissions.
        </para>
      </listitem> 

      <listitem>
        <para>
          At the command line, call 
        </para>
        <programlisting>
          MSCF16Control --serialfile your_serial_file
        </programlisting>

        <para>
          Doing so should bring up a window that looks like this.
        </para>
        <figure>
          <title>The MSCF16Control Graphical User Interface for USB</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/MSCF16Control-USBHowTo-0.png" align="center" format='PNG'/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          At this point, the user can manipulate the settings on the GUI, which
          directly update the device.
        </para> 
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>
      Saving and restoring state
    </title>

    <section>
      <title>Overview</title>

      <para>
        One of the special behaviors of this GUI is that the state is always
        saved at the end of a session (i.e. at exit) to a configuration file. This saves the entire state
        of the GUI: channel names and device settings. At startup of the subsequent
        session, the configuration file is read and only the channel
        names are restored. In this way, the existing device state prior to
        startup is left unalterred. The details of saving and loading are described below.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Saving the state</title>  
      <para>
        The state of the GUI can always be saved to a file by means of the "File
        > Save as..." drop-down menu button. The same thing happens at exit.
        There difference between the drop-down menu button and the save on exit
        operation is which file is saved to. When the drop-down menu is used,
        the user specifies the file that will be written to. At exit, the
        value of the --configfile command-line option will be used. 
      </para>
      
      <para>
        Saving the state of the gui
        produces a tcl script that can be executed for configuring the device
        exactly as the GUI would display it. This will 
        record the state of the device itself within the synchronization
        limitations of the application. To be more explicit, the only time the state written
        to file may not be identical to the device is if the user closes the
        GUI within the time window between the most recent change to the GUI and the
        time at which that most recent change would be communicated to the
        device. That is about a 300 ms time window. The best practice is therefore to allow
        the GUI to finish communicating prior to exiting.
      </para>

      <para>
        The script produced by a save as operation is actually a TCL script. It
        can be sourced in a TCL shell to set the state of the device independent
        of the GUI. This will work so long as:
      </para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The driver scripts are included in the TCLLIBPATH environment
            variable. These scripts should be usable if the user adds
            $DAQROOT/TclLibs to their TCLLIBPATH environment variable.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            The same settings for the communication protocol that were valid
            when the script was generated are still valid. In other words, if
            the GUI was launched with --serialfile set to /dev/ttyUSB0,
            then it must still be possible to write to the device through the
            /dev/ttyUSB0 file.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>
        If those requirements are satisfied, the script can be fed to a tclsh 
        program. That will transfer all of the state explicitly set in the 
        script to the device. To illustrate this further,
        if the configuration file is named mysettings.tcl, one should execute
        the following at the command line,
      </para>
      <programlisting>
        tclsh &lt; mysettings.tcl
      </programlisting>

    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Restoring the state</title>

      <para>
        Like saving, restoring implies that settings are loaded to the GUI.
        Because the device is tightly synchronized to the GUI, the loaded
        settings are immediately communicated to the device. For best results, 
        the user should load
        a tcl script that was generated by the GUI through a save as
        operation or at exit. If one knows what they are doing, they can
        certainly write their own configuration script by simply calling the
        same types of API calls as the scripts generated by the GUI.
      </para>

      <para>
        Loading the file causes the lines that are understood to be
        driver calls to be executed and loaded into the GUI. Furthermore, lines
        that set channel names (set ::MSCF16ChannelNames::chan0 name) are
        executed and read into the GUI. Other lines of code are not evaluated.
        This is actually very strict.
        For all of the parameters that are not set explicitly in the config file, the GUI will
        simply ignore them. 
      </para>

      <para>
        At startup, the state of only the channel names are restored from the
        file if it exists. The device state is only ever changed if the user
        explicitly uses the "Load settings..." menu button.
      </para>
    </section>

  </section>

</chapter>

<!-- /chapter -->
