<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Docbook XML 4.3//EN"
                      "file:///usr/share/xml/docbook/schema/dtd/4.3/docbookx.dtd" >
<book>
<article>

<refentry>
    <refmeta>
        <refentrytitle>CCBDCES8210ScalerTrigger nscl</refentrytitle>
        <manvolnum>3nscl</manvolnum>
    </refmeta>
    <refnamediv>
        <refname>CCBDCES8210ScalerTrigger</refname>
        <refpurpose>
            Provide a scaler trigger for the CES CBD8210 CAMAC
            parallel branch highway driver.
        </refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>
    <refsynopsisdiv>
        <para>
            You are strongly discouraged from using this module in
            new setups as the hardware cannot be serviced.
        </para>
        <para>
            #include <filename>&lt;CCBDCES8210ScalerTrigger.h&gt;</filename>
        </para>
        <programlisting>
class CCBDCES8210ScalerTrigger : public CScalerTrigger
{
public:
  CCBDCES8210ScalerTrigger(int b = 0);
  ~CCBDCES8210ScalerTrigger();


  // Overrides to produce a trigger:
public:
  virtual bool operator()();
  virtual void Initialize();
};

        </programlisting>
    </refsynopsisdiv>

    <refsect1>
        <title>DESCRIPTION</title>
        <para>
            Since the CES CBD8210 CAMAC parallel branch highway driver this
            software depends on is physically no longer maintainable, we do
            not recommend its use in new setups and strongly recommend existing
            setups migrate either to the Wiener VC32/CC32 module set, or away
            from CAMAC entirely if possible.
        </para>
        <para>
            This class provides the capability to drive scaler readouts off a
            NIM pulse into the IT4 input of a CES CBD 8210 CAMAC parallel branch
            highway driver.  The same module can simultaneously be used to supply
            event triggers as well.
        </para>
        <para>
            See ELECTRONICS SETUP below for a description of the trigger
            requirements of this module.
        </para>
    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
        <title>METHODS</title>
        <para>
            <function>CCBDCES8210ScalerTrigger</function>(
                  <classname>int</classname> <parameter>b</parameter>)
        </para>
        <para>
            Constructs a scaler trigger that is driven off the IT4 input of
            a CES CBD 8210 module (did we remember to tell you not to use this
            if you can help it yet?).  The <parameter>b</parameter> parameter
            is the branch number of the module.  The branch number also implies
            a VME crate number as follows.  The first 8 branches (numbered 0-7)
            are in VME crate 0,  The second 8 branches are in crate 1 etc.
            The branch selector on the front panel of the branch highway module
            determines the offset of the branch within the VME crate. Thus
            <parameter>b</parameter> = 9 is the module with branch 1 selected in
            VME crate 1.  The <parameter>b</parameter> parameter defaults to 0 if
            not supplied.
        </para>
        <para>
            <returnvalue>bool</returnvalue> <function>operator()</function>()
        </para>
        <para>
            This function is called by the framework to check for scaler triggers.
            normally you will not need to call this function.
        </para>
        <para>
            <returnvalue>void</returnvalue> <function>Initialize</function>()
        </para>
        <para>
            This function is called by the framework when the run is about to go
            active.  Normally you will not have to call this function.
        </para>
    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
        <title>ELECTRONICS SETUP</title>
        <para>
            The CES CBD8210 module (you do remember this module is obsolete right?),
            latches NIM logic pulses sent to the IT2 and IT4 inputs.  It is therefore
            only necessar to arrange a NIM logic true pulse to be presented at the IT4
            input when you want to trigger a scaler read.  It is not necessary
            to provide an external latch for this trigger.
        </para>
    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
        <title>SEE ALSO</title>
        <para>
            CScalerTrigger(3nscl), CCAENV262ScalerTrigger(3nscl), CCAENV977ScalerTrigger(3nscl),
            CTimedScalerTrigger(3nscl),
        </para>
        <para>
            <ulink url="http://docs.nscl.msu.edu/daq/appnotes/ScalerTriggerAppnote.pdf" />
            contains complete documentation that describes scaler triggers, how to
            establish them and how to write application specific ones.
        </para>
    </refsect1>
</refentry>



</article>
</book>
