<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Docbook XML 4.3//EN"
                      "file:///usr/share/xml/docbook/schema/dtd/4.3/docbookx.dtd" >
<book>
<article>

<refentry>
    <refmeta>
        <refentrytitle>CScalerTrigger nscl</refentrytitle>
        <manvolnum>3nscl</manvolnum>
    </refmeta>
    <refnamediv>
        <refname>CScalerTrigger</refname>
        <refpurpose>
            Abstract base classe for production readout scaler triggers.
        </refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>
    <refsynopsisdiv>
        <para>
            #include &lt;CScalerTrigger.h&gt;
        </para>
       <programlisting>
class CScalerTrigger
{
public:
  CScalerTrigger();
  virtual ~CScalerTrigger();
public:
  virtual bool operator()()  = 0;
  virtual void Initialize();
  virtual void Cleanup();
};

       </programlisting>
    </refsynopsisdiv>
    <refsect1>
        <title>DESCRIPTION</title>
        <para>
            For versions 8.4-pre5 and later of the production readout framework,
            arbitrary triggers can be used to induce scaler buffer reads.
            This is done by registering a <firstterm>Scaler Trigger</firstterm> object
            with the <classname>CExperiment</classname> object.
        </para>
        <para>
            <classname>CScalerTrigger</classname> is the abstract base class of the
            hierarchy of possible scaler trigger objects.  It defines the interfaces
            required of scaler trigger objects and, where possible, provides default
            implementations.
        </para>
    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
        <title>METHODS</title>
        <para>
        <function>operator()()</function>
        </para>
        <para>
            This function must be provided by concrete scaler triggers. If a concrete
            scaler trigger is registered with the <classname>CExperiment</classname>
            object as the scaler trigger, this member is periodically polled.
            It should return <constant>true</constant> if the scalers should be read
            and <constant>false</constant> if not.
        </para>
        <para>
            <function>Initialize()</function>
        </para>
        <para>
            This function is called whenever the run transitions to active.
            This may be either when the run first begins or when a paused run
            is resumed.  Default implementation is to do nothing.
        </para>
        <para>
            <function>Cleanup()</function>
        </para>
        <para>
            This function is called whenever the run goes inactive. This can be either
            due to the end of run or pausing a run.   The default implementation is
            to do nothing.
        </para>
    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
        <title>SEE ALSO</title>
        <para>
            CCAENV262ScalerTrigger(3nscl), CCAENV977ScalerTrigger(3nscl),
            CCAENCBDCES8210ScalerTrigger(3nscl), CTimedScalerTrigger(3nscl)
        </para>
        <para>
            <ulink url="http://docs.nscl.msu.edu/daq/appnotes/ScalerTriggerAppnote.pdf" />
            contains complete documentation that describes scaler triggers, how to
            establish them and how to write application specific ones.
        </para>
    </refsect1>
</refentry>



</article>
</book>
