<!-- chapter user-guide -->

<chapter>
  <title>Event Builder</title>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
      The NSCLDAQ event orderer program is a server that orders data items,
      a.k.a. fragments, submitted to it from an arbitrary number of clients,
      and outputs a single, ordered, merged stream on stdout. It deals with all
      fragments submitted to it generically, because all fragments wrap a
      payload with a consistent set of information contained in a header. The
      fragment header contains a timestamp, source ID, payload size, and
      barrier type. These pieces of information provide all of the necessary
      information for the event order to order its data and so that the event
      orderer can be used with any payload format.
    </para>

    <para>
      The pieces of information in the fragment header are used by the event
      orderer for different purposes and those will be covered briefly here.
      The timestamp is a 64-bit unsigned integer value that the fragments are
      ordered by. It typically represents a time value but could equally be an
      event number. The source ID is used to specify which internal queue  each
      set of committed fragments will be buffered in. It is not essential, but
      usually each client will submit their fragments to separate queues. The
      event fragments for each source ID must be time ordered.
    </para>

    <para>
      The payload size is the size of the data item  the fragment header
      describes. Its value is in units of bytes. The final piece of data, the
      barrier type, is an integer that specifies whether the fragment is to be
      used for synchronization. It can take any integer value but is treated by
      the orderer as a boolean. If it is zero, the fragment has no special
      meaning, but if it is nonzero, it indicates that a barrier
      synchronization is requested. Further details will be provided regarding
      the synchronization scheme later.  Normally this is used to indicate some
      event which performs gross synchronization between the data sources
      (begin run, end run etc).
    </para>

    <para>
      The client programs that submit data to the server are built using the
      <link linkend="chapter.evb-orderer-dev">event builder client
        framework</link>. In general, though, it is not necessary to implement a
      client when using the ring buffer system, because the client for ring
      items has already been provided as the <link
        linkend="sec_ringfragsrc">ringFragmentSource</link> program. This
      program simply reads ring items from a ring buffer, prepends fragment
      headers to them, and then submits them to the server. 
    </para>

    <para>
      The ordered fragments are output whenever the server is able to
      unambiguously determine that its output stream will be ordered or when
      one client has not submitted data for a user-definable amount of time,
      the build window. The queues are processed for output
      whenever new input is received and every second.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Using the event builder</title>

    <para>
      In NSCLDAQ, the standard way to set up the event builder is to use the
      ReadoutGUI. At the moment, the ReadoutGUI provides support for the event
      builder through the ReadoutCallouts.tcl script. You can learn more about
      this script in the ReadoutGUI section of the manual, but for this
      situation you only need to know that it is a Tcl script that is sourced by
      the ReadoutGUI when starting up. We can use it to enable the event builder
      and configure it for use. The recommended method for
      setting this up is to use the event builder callout bundle. Doing so
      reduces the amount of Tcl that needs to be added and ensures that the
      event builder recovers properly from errors. Simply add the following few
      lines to your ReadoutCallouts.tcl script:
    </para>

    <programlisting>
package require evbcallouts

::EVBC::useEventBuilder

proc OnStart {} {
  ::EVBC::initialize -restart false -glombuild true -glomdt 123 -destring evbout
}
    </programlisting>

    <para>
      When the "Start" button is pushed in the ReadoutGUI, this will add a set
      of controls for the event builder to the bottom of it. The option values
      provided here specify that the event builder will not restart on each new
      run (-restart), event correlation will be enabled (-glombuild), events
      within 123 clock ticks of each other will be correlated (-glomdt), and the
      output will be put into the ring named evbout on localhost.  If you prefer
      to change any of these parameters, feel free to do so. You can read more
      details about the callouts in the <link
        linkend="chapter.evbcallouts-dev">developer documentation</link> as well
      in the <link linkend="man-3evb">man pages</link>.
    </para>

    <para>
      The next thing that you need to do register clients
      to the event builder, more specifically the event orderer. Assuming that
      the data being committed to the event builder are ring items, the client
      will be the ringFragmentSource. There is a convenience API call
      provided to assist in registering the ringFragmentSource called
      EVBC::registerRingSource. We will make use of it. However first a
      timestamp extractor librrary must be created for the ringFragmentSource.
      This library contains a function that will define how to extract a
      timestamp from the body of a PHYSICS_EVENT item. You can find an example
      of how to create one at the <link
        linkend="sec_ringfragsrc">ringFragmentSource documentation</link>.
    </para>
    <para>
      The registerRingSource proc has the form:
    </para>
    <programlisting>
::EVBC::registerRingSource sourceURI tstamplib id info
    </programlisting>

    <para>
      where <literal>sourceURI</literal> is the full URI specifying the ring
      buffer to read data from, <literal>tstamplib</literal> is the path to the
      compiled timestamp extractor library, <literal>id</literal> is the source
      id for the data, and <literal>info</literal> is a string that describes To
      illustrate how this works, consider an experiment in which the data
      produced by some silicon detectors are read out by a single Readout
      program in the system. The outputted data from this Readout are put into
      the "sidet0" ring buffer on localhost, and a timestamp can be properly
      extracted from each datum by the timestamp function recently compiled into
      the libtstamp.so shared library. Being the first client registered, we
      choose to label this stream of data with source id 0. We also want to
      associate a human readable description of ?Si Dets? with it. In this
      scenario, the line that would be added to the ReadoutCallouts.tcl would be
      <programlisting>
::EVBC::registerRingSource tcp://localhost/sidet0 /path/to/libtstamp.so 0 "Si Dets"
      </programlisting>
    </para>

    <para>
      Putting this all together you would have a ReadoutCallouts.tcl that looks
      like this:
    </para>

    <programlisting>
package require evbcallouts

::EVBC::useEventBuilder

proc OnStart {} {
  ::EVBC::initialize -restart false -glombuild true -glomdt 123
}

EVBC::registerRingSource tcp://localhost/sidet0 /path/to/libtstamp.so 0 "Si Dets"
    </programlisting>

    <para>
      Be aware that you need to add a registerRingSource line for every client
      that will be submitting data to the event builder.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>More detail on when the fragments are ouptutted</title>

    <para>
      Let's dig a little deeper into the way the event orderer determines when
      to output data. Knowing this logic will help understand its behavior,
      which may otherwise seem unexpected in some circumstances. The handling
      of non-barriers will be addressed first and then barriers second. 
    </para>

    <para>
      For the case of non-barriers, the most basic principle that one should
      remember about the event builder is that whenever all input queues have
      data, ordered data can be emitted. Fragments will be outputted until at
      least one queue does not have data. This is the sensible approach because
      fragments may simply have not reached the orderer yet.
    </para>

    <para>
      If one of the data sources does not receive new fragments, the data from
      active sources will remain in the queue for the duration of the build
      window. All fragments that have resided in a queue longer than the build
      window are then are outputted in order of their timestamps. So if a
      client ceases to commit fragments to the event orderer, the orderer will
      cease to output data until a time equal to the build window has passed.
      At that point, the event orderer will resume outputting data. If the
      stalled client then resumes contributing fragments and those have
      timestamps that should have been outputted earlier, these fragments are
      called late. This is a recoverable error condition. The default build
      window width is 20 seconds. Furthermore, the event orderer will not output data until 2
      seconds have elapsed since the first fragment was submitted.  This is
      intended to allow all sources time to submit their first fragment to the
      orders as it is that action that creates a data source queue.
    </para>

    <para>
      Barriers are treated differently. Recall that a barrier event implies
      synchronization between the data sources. Therefore when a barrier is
      detected in one queue, no more fragments are outputted from that queue until
      a barrier is found in all other queues. Once the barrier is complete, all
      barriers are output and then normal operations are resumed. There is an
      extended time window, four times the build window, during which queues
      will wait for a barrier to complete before resuming output. If that
      window passes without establishing a complete barrier, the barrier will
      be considered incomplete and the barrier fragments seen so far will be
      flushed, the incomplete barrier is logged and then normal operation
      resumes. Barrier synchronization is agnostic to the specific type of each
      barrier.  If there is a barrier in all queues, the synchronization is
      complete. However, if the type of barriers are different, the barriers
      statistics presented to the user will report that the barrier was
      heterogeneous. On the other hand, if all barriers are the same type, the
      completed barrier will be considered homogeneous. In general, a healthy
      set of data streams should produce complete, homogeneous barriers.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Fragments and Data Format</title>

    <para>
      As has already been discussed, the event builder does not deal with ring
      items. Instead it handles fragments. Fragments are generic and are
      purposefully independent of the ring item data format so that the event
      builder can work with any type of data format the same way. This section
      will describe a bit more about the fragment as is useful for the standard
      user.
    </para>

    <section>
      <title>Anatomy of a fragment</title>
      <para>
        A fragment consists of a header and body just like the ring item. In the
        parlance of the event builder, though, the body is referred to as the
        payload. There are 4 elements in the fragment header a timestamp, source
        id, payload size, and barrier type. The layout of the entire fragment is
        as follows:
      </para>

      <table frame="all">
        <title>Fragment header</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry/>
              <entry>Description</entry>
              <entry>Size (bytes)</entry>
            </row>
          </thead> 
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry morerows="3">Header</entry>
              <entry>Timestamp</entry>
              <entry>8</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Source ID</entry>
              <entry>4</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Payload size</entry>
              <entry>4</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Barrier type</entry>
              <entry>4</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Payload</entry>
              <entry>Data...</entry>
              <entry>(Payload size)</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Output Format</title>

      <para>
        The event builder outputs standard NSCLDAQ 11.0 ring items. For
        non-PHYSICS_EVENT items, the outputted items are the same are inputted.
        Basically, the fragment headers that were appended to them by the client
        are stripped off before the data is outputted.
      </para>
      <para>
        The format of PHYSICS_EVENTS are a bit more interesting. For physics
        events, the event builder will create "built" events. A built event is
        just a standard PHYSICS_EVENT. However, the body is constructed of the
        correlated fragments. It begins with a 32-bit
        integer specifying the entire size of the body and the remainder is a
        series of one or more fragments. There is no information specifying how
        many fragments are present without processing the body. Because each
        fragment specifies its payload size, the user can compute how many
        fragments are present merely by traversing the body and keeping track of
        the number of bytes and fragments traversed. Once the entire number of
        bytes in the body have been traversed, the user will know how many
        fragments are present.
      </para>

      <para>
        From experience, the built body seems to be hard for many people to get
        their head around. One of the confusing things is that the built event
        is a ring item filled with fragments whose payloads are
        <emphasis>complete</emphasis> ring items themselves. Most of the time,
        users are shielded from the details of the ring item header and body
        header and only see the body proper. The built ring item however
        makes these plainly visible. This leads to confusion because typically
        the body header in each embedded ring item and the fragment
        header will have likely have the same information. It will look like there are
        duplicates of the same information in the body. The timestamp sometimes
        appears three times, because the number in the body header and fragment
        header are usually derived from a number in raw data. Though this has
        caused some users to panic when trying to understand their data, it is
        typically the result of a misinterpretation. Don't be fooled.
      </para>
      <para>
        To make all of this a bit more plain, a diagram of the
        built ring item's body is shown when it contains two fragments.
      </para>
      <table frame="all">
        <title>Body of Built PHYSICS_EVENT</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>High-Level Description</entry>
              <entry>Lower-Level Description</entry>
              <entry>Size (bytes)</entry>
            </row>
          </thead> 
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>Body size</entry>
              <entry>Number of bytes in body</entry>
              <entry>4</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry morerows="3">Fragment #0</entry>
              <entry>Fragment Header</entry>
              <entry>20</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Ring Item Header</entry>
              <entry>8</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Ring Item Body Header</entry>
              <entry>4 or 20</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Ring Item Body</entry>
              <entry>Determined by Readout program and user</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry morerows="3">Fragment #1</entry>
              <entry>Fragment Header</entry>
              <entry>20</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Ring Item Header</entry>
              <entry>8</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Ring Item Body Header</entry>
              <entry>4 or 20</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Ring Item Body</entry>
              <entry>Determinable by Readout program and user</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>

      <para>
        Be aware that this is the format regardless of whether you choose to
        correlate data or not. When the event builder is not correlating, i.e.
        not building, the built events will always hold only 1 fragment in the
        body.  Otherwise, there may be more than one fragment.
      </para>
      <para>
        Finally, the built ring item will be produced with a body header, the
        above table shows the format immediately following the body header. The
        timestamp in the body header will be determined based on the timestamp
        protocol of the event builder. The protocol allows you to choose whether
        the entire built event is labeled with the earliest, latest, or average
        timestamp of the correlated fragments. Also, the source id will be set
        according to user preference.  This allows for multiple stages of event
        building to be accomplished.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>

<!-- /chapter -->
