<!-- manpage 1daq -->

<refentry id="manpage.dumper">
  <refmeta>
     <refentrytitle>dumper</refentrytitle>
     <manvolnum>1daq</manvolnum>
  </refmeta>
  <refnamediv>
     <refname>dumper</refname>
     <refpurpose>Produce a formatted dump of event data.</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  
  <refsynopsisdiv>
    <cmdsynopsis>
	<command>
dumper <replaceable>?options?</replaceable>
	</command>
    </cmdsynopsis>
  </refsynopsisdiv>
  <refsect1>
     <title>DESCRIPTION</title>
     <para>
	The
        <command>dumper</command>
        command produces formatted dumps of data produced by the NSCL DAQ
        system.  The format of the dump, and some of the basic principles of
        operation are described in the chapter
        <link linkend="ch.dumper">Dumping events from ringbuffer or from file</link>.
     </para>
     <para>
        The command line parameters for the dumper are all options.  These are described in
        OPTIONS below.  The command
        <command>dumper --help</command> will also provide brief help.
     </para>
  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
     <title>
	OPTIONS
     </title>
     <para>
        The description below provides only the long (double dashed) forms of each
        option.  Single letter (single dashed) forms exist.  Use the
        <option>--help</option> option to get a table of options that shows those.
     </para>
     <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	    <term><option>--count</option>=<replaceable>int</replaceable></term>
	    <listitem>
		<para>
                    Requests that the program exit after it has printed
                    <replaceable>int</replaceable> items.
		</para>
	    </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
            <term><option>--exclude</option>=<replaceable>type-list</replaceable></term>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Requests that any items in the <parameter>type-list</parameter>
                    be supressed from the output.  In the case of ring buffer data,
                    this determines how the ring filter predicate is constructed.
                    In the case of a file data source, the data source must read and
                    skip the data.
                </para>
                <para>
                    The <parameter>type-list</parameter> is a comma separated
                    list of item types.  Any mix of integer and symbolic types
                    can be used. See
                    <filename>DataFormat.h</filename>
                    for a list of the symbolic and integer type codes known
                    to the NSCLDAQ.  User generated types can be excluded
                    as well by specifying their integer type codes.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
            <term><option>--help</option></term>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Provides a quick help on the program options.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
            <term><option>--skip</option>=<replaceable>int</replaceable></term>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Skips <replaceable>int</replaceable> items before starting
                    to print items.  The items skipped must have been printable
                    in the first place (e.g. not on the <option>--exclude</option>
                    list nor, in the on-line case, would have been omitted
                    due to sampling).
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
            <term><option>--sample</option>=<replaceable>type-list</replaceable></term>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Requests that the item types in <parameter>type-list</parameter>
                    be sampled.  This is only legal for ring buffer data sources.
                    Sampled item types are only presented if receiving them would
                    leave the ring empty of other items.
                </para>
                <para>
                The <parameter>type-list</parameter> is a comma separated
                list of item types.  Any mix of integer and symbolic types
                can be used. See
                <filename>DataFormat.h</filename>
                for a list of the symbolic and integer type codes known
                to the NSCLDAQ.  User generated types can be excluded
                as well by specifying their integer type codes.
            </para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
            <term><option>--scaler-width</option>=<replaceable>bits</replaceable></term>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Specifies the width of scaler counters in bits.  Unused
                    bits will be masked off prior to output.  This is useful for
                    some CAMAC readout systems where scaler values can hav additional
                    bits at the top end that are not meaningful.
                    <parameter>bits</parameter> must be a positive number
                    that is at most <literal>32</literal>.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        
        <varlistentry>
            <term><option>--source</option>=<replaceable>URL</replaceable></term>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Specifies the data source.  If omitted, the ring buffer named
                    after the current user is used.  If the URL is a
                    <literal>file</literal> protocol, the file specified by the
                    path string is opened and dumped.
                    If the URl is a <literal>tcp</literal> protocol,
                    the host and path refer to a ring buffer and that ring buffer
                    is the source of the data.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
            <term><option>--version</option></term>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Prints out the version of the program.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
     </variablelist>
  </refsect1>


</refentry>

<!-- /manpage -->
