<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>


<chapter>
    <title>bufdump quickstart guide</title>
    <para>
        This chapter will give you the minimum information you need
        to start using the bufdump program.  In this chapter you will learn:
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><para>How to start bufdump</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>How to select a source of buffers</para> </listitem>
            <listitem><para>How to get buffers from the data source </para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>How to access the program's online help</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <important>
        <para>The procedure below assumes that the
            NSCLDAQ utility programs are in the your PATH.
            At the NSCL this means that the PATH environment
            variable includes an entry for /usr/opt/utilities/current/bin
        </para>
    </important>

    <procedure>
        <title>Starting bufdump</title>
        <para>
            To start the bufdump program:
        </para>
        <step performance="required">
            <para>Login to a system on which the bufdump program has been
                installed </para>
        </step>
        <step performance="required">
            <para>If necessary start a terminal window</para>
        </step>
        <step performance="required">
            <para>Type:</para>
            <screen>
                <prompt> bash$ </prompt><command> bufdump </command>
            </screen>
        </step>
    </procedure>
    <para> If you have successfully followed these steps, the bufdump
        window will appear as shown below:
        <screenshot>
            <screeninfo>Screenshot of bufdump main window</screeninfo>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject><imagedata fileref="bufdump.gif" format="GIF" />
                </imageobject>
                <imageobject><imagedata fileref="bufdump.eps" format="EPS" />
                </imageobject>
                <caption>Screen shot of the bufdump program's main window
                </caption>
            </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
    </para>
    <procedure>
        <title>Selecting a data source</title>
        <para>This procedure will show you how to select an offline
            data source for detailed information about selecting
            data sources see the discussion of the
            <menuchoice>
                <guimenu>File</guimenu>
                <guimenuitem>Open...</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>
            command in <link linkend="chap3">Chapter 3: The file menu</link>.
        </para>
        <step performance="required">
            <para>
                Click the File menu on the menubar at the top of the
                bufdump main window.
            </para>
        </step>
        <step performance="required">
            <para>Click the Open... menu entry in the File menu.
            </para>
            <para> This should result in the data source dialog box
                like the one shown below.
                <screenshot>
                    <screeninfo>Screenshot of the open data source dialog</screeninfo>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject><imagedata fileref="open.gif" format="GIF" />
                        </imageobject>
                        <imageobject><imagedata fileref="open.eps" format="EPS" />
                        </imageobject>
                        <caption>Screen shot of the open data source dialog.
                        </caption>
                    </mediaobject>
                </screenshot>
            </para>
        </step>
        <step performance="required">
            <para>Use the lower part of the dialog box to navigate to the directory that has
                your event files and click on the event file you want to
                examine.
            </para>
        </step>
        <step performance="required">
            <para>Click the Ok button.  The dialog box will be removed from
                the screen.
            </para>
        </step>

    </procedure>
    <important>
        <para>The procedure below assumes that you have already selected a
            data source.
        </para>
    </important>
    <procedure>
        <title>Stepping through the event source</title>
        <step performance="required">
            <para>Locate the arrow button pointing right at the lower left of
                the bufdump main window</para>
        </step>
        <step performance="required">
            <para>Click the right arrow button.
                The bufdump program will read the next buffer from
                the event source, decode the buffer and display the
                decoded buffer in the middle part of the bufdump main window.
            </para>
        </step>
        <step>
            <para>Repeatedly clicking the right arrow button will
                tell bufdump to read subseqeunt buffers from the data source,
                decode and display them.  Bufdump will hold several buffers in
                memory.  As needed, the middle window will grow scroll bars
                to allow you to scroll back and forth through the
                data that has been decoded and displayed.
            </para>
        </step>
    </procedure>

<tip>
    <para>The bufdump program is quite powerful.  If you want to learn
        more about what bufdump can do, and how to use it like an expert,
        read the remainder of this manual.
    </para>
</tip>

</chapter>
