<!-- chapter device-support -->

<chapter>
  <title>
    ULM Trigger GUI    
  </title>

  <para>
    A firmware for the LeCroy 2367 Universal Logic Module written by Daniel
    Bazin turns the device into a trigger processing unit commonly referred to
    as the S800 ULM Trigger Box. This device has numerous configurable
    parameters that can be used to determine how and when a live trigger is
    formed from a set of triggers. NSCLDAQ provides support for configuring and
    reading out this device and also a mechanism for controlling it remotely as
    a slow-controlled device. The latter mechanism is a GUI called the
    ULMTriggerGUI and will be the subject of this documentation. The
    ULMTriggerGUI is heavily geared towards its use in the S800 and has many
    controls specifically labeled as corresponding to the S800. The aim of this
    documentation is not to detail all of the various features for use, but
    rather how to set up and launch an instance of the program as well as
    explain a bit about the saving and restoring state to and from files. 
  </para>

  <section>
    <title>Configuring CCUSBReadout for Remote Communication</title>

    <para>
      The ULMTriggerGUI makes use of the ccusbcamac TCL package to send remote
      NAF commands to a CCUSBReadout slow-controls server. The first step to
      use the ULMTriggerGUI is to ensure that the CCUSBReadout is configured to
      receive remote CCUSB requests. The only thing that is required is that a
      slow controls module of type "ccusb" be loaded. To do that you need to
      add the following line to your CCUSBReadout's ctlconfig.tcl script.
    </para>

    <programlisting>
Module create ccusb remoteHandler
    </programlisting>

    <para>
      Depending on the version of NSCLDAQ that you are using, this may or may
      not be necessary because in recent versions the remote handler is
      preloaded into the CCUSBReadout program. However, it is simplest to just
      add the single line above.
    </para>

  </section>

  <section>
    <title>
      Launching the ULMTriggerGUI
    </title>

    <para>
      It is first and foremost important to realize that the ULMTriggerGUI is a
      client of the CCUSBReadout slow controls server. In that sense, there is
      no way that the ULMTriggerGUI can run without the CCUSBReadout running
      first. So you must launch a CCUSBReadout program that has been fed the
      ctlconfig.tcl script from the previous section before you launch the
      ULMTriggerGUI. Depending on whether other processes are running that
      might have control over port 27000 already, you may have to explicitly
      specify a port to listen for connections using the --port option. Once
      the CCUSBReadout program is running, you can then proceed to launch the
      ULMTriggerGUI.
    </para>

    <para>
      The ULMTriggerGUI requires only a few pieces of information to launch.
      They are:
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Hostname of the computer running the slow controls server</para> 
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Port on which the slow controls server listens for connections</para> 
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Slow controls module name</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Slot number that the LeCroy 2367 ULM module resides</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Name of ringbuffer to listen for state transitions on</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Configuration file name</para>
      </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>

    <para>
      In general, these are given reasonable default values so that you can
      typically forego specifying all of the options except for the
      slow-controls module name and the slot number. By default, the host name
      is given as "localhost", the port number is provided 27000, and the
      ringbuffer name is given tcp://localhost/USERNAME. Here the USERNAME is a
      placeholder for your user name. Note that only ring buffers on localhost
      can be specified. Only the slow controls module must be specified because
      there is no a priori way of knowing the name of the module you have
      loaded into you ctlconfig.tcl. If we continue the example from the
      previous section, you would specify the value passed to -module as
      remoteHandler.
    </para>

    <para> 
      Putting this all together, we can launch the ULMTriggerGUI to control a
      ULM in slot 10 read out by a CCUSBReadout running locally, listening on
      port 27000, and outputting data to tcp://localhost/USERNAME by either
      entering:
    </para>

    <programlisting>
$DAQBIN/ULMTriggerGUI --module remoteHandler --slot 10
    </programlisting>

    <para>
      or
    </para>

    <programlisting>
$DAQBIN/ULMTriggerGUI --moduel remoteHandler --port 27000 --host localhost --ring USERNAME --slot 10
    </programlisting>

    <para>
      After executing those commands, you should see a window pop up that looks like:
      <figure>
        <title>Screenshot of ULMTriggerGUI</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/ulmtrigger_startup.png" align="center" format='PNG'/>
          </imageobject>
          <caption>
            <para>
              Screenshot of the ULMTriggerGUI after startup.
            </para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Overview of Basic Operation</title>

    <para>
      The ULMTriggerGUI state is "directly connected", or tightly synchronized,
      to the state of the ULM it is associated with.  For that reason, it is
      only safe to manipulate the GUI elements while a run is not active. To
      protect against modifying the settings during a run, the ULMTriggerGUI
      will lock when a BEGIN_RUN item is observed in the ring buffer it is
      monitoring and only unlock when an END_RUN item is observed. 
    </para>
    <para>
      A consequence of the GUI being tightly synchronized is that the GUI will
      display the state of the ULM at all times after the start up and an
      "Update from Module" has been pressed. It will only display a different
      state than the ULM 1) before you press "Update from Module" after
      starting it and 2) after you press "Read from File".
    </para>

    <para>
      One of the important features of the ULMTriggerGUI is the ability to save
      and restore the state of the GUI to a file. This file is then used to
      configure the ULM at the start of runs in the S800 DAQ. To write the
      state of the GUI to a file, you simply need to press the "Save to File".
      If the --configfile option has not been set, a file browser for you to
      choose the location to save the file. This will only occur the first time
      and the selection will be used in all future occurrences. If you provided
      the --configfile option, then the file you provided will be used and no
      browser will pop up. 
    </para>

    <para>
      There is some red text next to the "Save to File" button that says "Save
      to make Active!".  This is a bit of a red herring and should be
      understood properly. Because the GUI is tightly synchronized to the ULM,
      any change to the GUI actively changes the state of the ULM. However, the
      S800 DAQ uses the configuration file generated by this GUI to configure
      the device at the start of the run. So when a run begins in the S800DAQ,
      the ULM is configured based on the settings of the GUI the last time
      "Save to File" was pressed. Of course, this is all dependent upon
      configuration of the ULM being done in a manner similar to the S800DAQ
      and also that the "Save to File" writes to the same file as the
      configuration procedures reads from. As I said in the beginning, this GUI
      is designed in a manner that is S800 centric. To boil this down, "Save to
      make Active!" should be read as "Save to make Active during run if you
      use the file to configure your ULM at the start of each run!"
    </para>

  </section>

</chapter>

<!-- /chapter -->
