<!-- chapter utilities -->

<chapter>
    <title>The Scaler Display Program.</title>
    <para>
        With NSCLDAQ-11.0 and the ability to merge data from multiple data
        sources, a new scaler display has been written to accomodate the
        special needs of this system.  Specifically the new program:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>
            Can accept data from multiple rings (or from the output of the event builder).
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
            Can support data sources that emit scaler data at differing rates.
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
            Provides better support for non-incremental scalers and narrow (less than 32 bit wide)
            scaler channels.
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
            Does not require the <application>sclclient</application> helper program.
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
            Provides a high degree of compatibility with ordinary configuration files for the
            NSCLDAQ-10.x and earlier versions of the scaler display.
        </para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
        The remainder of this chapter describes:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>
            How to run the scaler display program.
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
            The basic elements that make up a scaler display configuration file.
        </para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
        For reference information see the
        <link linkend='daq1_scalerdisplay11' endterm='daq1_scalerdisplay11_title' /> manpage.
    </para>
    <section>
        <title>Running the scaler display program.</title>
        <para>
            The scaler display program needs two pieces of information to operate:
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem><para>
                    A list of one or more rings from which data will be taken.    
                </para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>
                    A description of how to present the data it receives to you.
                </para></listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <para>
            The set of input rings is specified by defining the environment variable
            <literal>SCALER_RING</literal> to be a space separated list of ring URIs.
            Recall that the form of a ring URI is:
            <literal>tcp://</literal><replaceable>hostname</replaceable><literal>/</literal><replaceable>ringname</replaceable>
            where <replaceable>hostname</replaceable> is the name of the host in which the ring is defined
            and <replaceable>ringname</replaceable> is the name of the ring itself.
        </para>
        <para>
            The following bash command line defines <literal>SCALER_RING</literal> to accept data
            from the local ring <literal>fox1</literal> and a remote ring living in
            <literal>spdaq22</literal> called <literal>fox2</literal>:
        </para>
        <informalexample>
            <programlisting>
export SCALER_RING="tcp://localhost/fox1 tcp://spdaq22/fox2"
            </programlisting>
        </informalexample>
        <para>
            A description of how to process the data from the input rings is
            provided by a configuration file.  The next section will give more
            details on the form of the configuration file.  The configuration file
            is a command line parameter supplied when the program is invoked.
        </para>
        <para>
            The scaler display program itself lives in the <filename>bin</filename>
            directory of the NSCLDAQ installation tree.  The <filename>daqstart.bash</filename>
            script, in the top level of the NSCLDAQ installation tree can be used
            to define several useful environment variables.  If that script has been
            sourced (we recommend you source it in your <filename>.bashrc</filename>
            script), the following command line will start the scaler program:
        </para>
        <informalexample>
            <programlisting>
$DAQBIN/ScalerDisplay myscalers.def
            </programlisting>
        </informalexample>
        <para>
            Where <filename>myscalers.def</filename> is the definition file.
        </para>
        <para>
            The scaler display program will produce several files at the end of each run:
        </para>
        <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><filename>run</filename><replaceable>nnnn</replaceable><filename>.report</filename></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        A human readable report for run number <replaceable>nnnn</replaceable>.
                        Note that the run number part of the filename will have leading zeroes to fill
                        it out to four digits.  In the event your experiment has more than <literal>9999</literal>
                        runs, an additional digit will be added to the run number part of the filename.
                    </para>
                    
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><filename>run</filename><replaceable>nnnn</replaceable><filename>.csv</filename></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Contains the same information as the <filename>.report</filename> file but
                        in CSV format, so that it can easily be sucked into a program
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><filename>run</filename><replaceable>nnnn</replaceable><filename>-stripchart.ps</filename></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        A postscript rendering of the strip chart (if it is enabled) at the end of the run.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
        <section>
            <title>Sample report file</title>
            <para>
                Below the first few lines of a <filename>.report</filename> file created at the
                end of the run by the scaler display program.
            </para>
            <informalexample>
                <programlisting>
Run     :  905
Title   :  some new title
Started :  Mon Sep 22 13:54:31 EDT 2014
Ended   :  Mon Sep 22 13:57:17 EDT 2014
Elapsed : 0 00:02:46

+---------+-----+------------+------------+
|Name     |Total|Average Rate|Rate std-dev|
+---------+-----+------------+------------+
|channel00|5269 |31.61       |21.74       |
|channel01|5279 |31.67       |21.86       |
|channel02|5286 |31.72       |21.85       |
|channel03|5284 |31.70       |21.82       |
|channel04|5290 |31.74       |21.82       |
|channel05|5298 |31.79       |21.80       |
|channel06|5296 |31.78       |21.77       |
|channel07|5304 |31.82       |21.77       |
|channel08|5308 |31.85       |21.78       |
|channel09|5306 |31.84       |21.76       |
|channel10|5312 |31.87       |21.76       |
|channel11|5312 |31.87       |21.77       |
|channel12|5317 |31.90       |21.77       |
|channel13|5318 |31.91       |21.77       |
...                    
                </programlisting>
            </informalexample>
            <para>Note that typicall you will have chosen more useful channel names (left most column)</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Sample csv file</title>
            <para>
                Below are the first few lines of a <filename>.csv</filename> file produced
                by the scaler program at the end of a run:
            </para>
            <informalexample>
                <programlisting>
905,some new title,Mon Sep 22 13:54:31 EDT 2014,Mon Sep 22 13:57:17 EDT 2014,166
channel00,5269,31.614126456505826,21.737690006796004
channel01,5279,31.674126696506786,21.862983433929543
channel02,5286,31.71612686450746,21.85259265477174
channel03,5284,31.704126816507266,21.82050687447798
channel04,5290,31.740126960507844,21.82339257631644
channel05,5298,31.78812715250861,21.803205011543277
channel06,5296,31.77612710450842,21.774543936089657
channel07,5304,31.824127296509186,21.771400477541533
                </programlisting>
            </informalexample>
            <para>The first line is a header that contains</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem><para>
                    The run number
                </para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>
                    The title string
                </para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>
                    The date and time at which the run started.
                </para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>
                    The date and time at which the run ended.
                </para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>
                    The total length of the run in seconds.
                </para></listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>
                Subsequent lines of the file contain information about each scaler in order:
            </para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem><para>
                    The name you assigned to the scaler channel.
                </para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>
                    The total number of counts in that scaler over the length of the run.
                </para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>
                    The average count rate in the scaler over the length of the run.
                </para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>
                    The standard deviation in the count rate over the length of the run.
                    Note that for the examples, the scaler rates are contrived and the
                    standard deviation is artificially large for the average rate.
                </para></listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>The configuration file</title>
        <para>
            The scaler configuration file:
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><para>
                Provides a meaningful name to each scaler channel you care about.
            </para></listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Describes a set of scaler display pages (tabs in a tabbed notebook)
                    and what to display in each page.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Optionally defines a stripchart and what is plotted on that
                    chart.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>
            A configuration file is just a Tcl script.  A few extra commands have been
            added that allow that script to define the objects needed by the scaler
            program:
        </para>
        <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><command>channel</command></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Associates a meaningful name with a scaler channel index
                        from a specific source id.  In addition, this command can
                        define alarm levels, indicate whether the scaler is read incrementally
                        or reset after each read and indicate the number of bits wide the
                        scaler data from that channel are.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><command>page</command></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Defines a scaler display page.  The command defines both  a page
                        title (long form) and the short form which is used to reference this page
                        in other commands.  The short form is also used to label the scaler page's
                        tab in the scaler display tabbed notebook.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><command>display_single</command></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Adds a line to a page that displays a single scaler.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><command>display_ratio</command></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Adds a line to a page that displays a pair of scalers and their
                        ratio of rates/totals.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>blankd</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Adds a blank line to a scaler page.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><command>stripparam</command></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Enables stripcharting if it is not already enabled, and plots the rate
                        of a scaler on the stripchart.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><command>stripratio</command></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Enables stripcharting if it is not already enabled, and plots the
                        ratio f the rates of two scalers on the strip chart.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><command>stripconfig</command></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Allows aspects of the strip chart to be configured.  Specifically
                        the number of seconds of history that are displayed on the
                        time axis.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
        <section>
            <title>Sample scaler configuration file.</title>
            <para>
                The scaler definition file below shows all of the features of scaler
                definition files:
            </para>
            <example>
                <title>Scaler Definition files</title>
                <programlisting>
page page1 {Source 1}                            <co id='scalerdef_page' />
page page2 {Source 2}


for {set i 0} {$i &lt; 32} {incr i} {           <co id='scalerdef_itstcl' />
    set name [format channel%02d $i]
    channel $name $i.1                          <co id='scalerdef_channel' />
    display_single page1 $name                  <co id='scalerdef_single'  />

    set name [format src2%02d $i]
    channel -incremental 0 $name  $i.2         <co id='scalerdef_source2' />
    display_single page2  $name
}
page ratio ratios
blank         ratio                          <co id='scalerdef_blank' />
display_ratio ratio channel00 src200         <co id='scalerdef_displayratio' />

stripparam channel00                         <co id='scalerdef_stripparam' />
stripparam src200
stripratio channel00 src200                  <co id='scalerdef_stripratio' />
stripconfig -timeaxis 1200                   <co id='scalerdef_stripconfig' />

                </programlisting>
            </example>
            <calloutlist>
                <callout arearefs='scalerdef_page'>
                    <para>
                        The <command>page</command> command creates a new scaler
                        display page.  The first parameter is the tab name and is
                        also used to refer to the page in other display commands.
                        The second parameter is the title and is displayed at the top
                        of the page.
                    </para>
                </callout>
                <callout arearefs='scalerdef_itstcl'>
                    <para>
                        This structure shows that the scaler definition files are
                        just Tcl scripts.  The <command>for</command> command
                        is used to make the definition of several consecutive
                        channels with patterned names easy.
                    </para>
                </callout>
                <callout arearefs='scalerdef_channel'>
                    <para>
                        The <command>channel</command> command defines a scaler channel.
                        The first parameter is the name associated with that channel.
                        The second parameter identifies which channel.  The channel
                        identifier is of the form <replaceable>index</replaceable>.<replaceable>source</replaceable> where
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        On each pass through the loop, this command will create a new channel definition
                        for data source 1.
                    </para>
                </callout>
                <callout arearefs='scalerdef_single'>
                    <para>
                        Defines a line on <literal>page2</literal> of the scaler display
                        that displays the single scaler defined in the previous line.
                    </para>
                </callout>
                <callout arearefs='scalerdef_source2'>
                    <para>
                        Creates a channel definition for data source 2 on each pass through the loop.
                        These channels come from a data source whose scalers are not read incrementally
                        (<literal>-incremental 0</literal>).
                    </para>
                </callout>
                <callout arearefs='scalerdef_blank'>
                    <para>
                        Adds a blank line to the <literal>ratio</literal> page.
                    </para>
                </callout>
                <callout arearefs='scalerdef_displayratio'>
                    <para>
                        Adds a line to the <literal>ratio</literal> page that
                        displays both <literal>channel00</literal> <literal>src200</literal>.
                        In addition the ratios of the scaler rates and totals for these
                        two scalers are displayed with <literal>channel00</literal> as the
                        numerator.
                    </para>
                </callout>
                <callout arearefs='scalerdef_stripparam'>
                    <para>
                        Creates the strip chart display by defining a trace of the
                        rate in the <literal>channel00</literal> scaler channel.
                    </para>
                </callout>
                <callout arearefs='scalerdef_stripratio'>
                    <para>
                        Creates a strip chart trace that displays the ratio of
                        rates of <literal>channel00</literal> (the numerator) and
                        <literal>src200</literal>.
                    </para>
                </callout>
                <callout arearefs='scalerdef_stripconfig'>
                    <para>
                        Configures the strip chart time axis to display the most recent
                        <literal>1200</literal> seconds of trace information.
                    </para>
                </callout>
                
            </calloutlist>
            
        </section>
    </section>
    
</chapter>

<!-- /chapter -->

<!-- manpage 1daq -->

<refentry id='daq1_scalerdisplay11'>
    <refmeta>
        <refentrytitle id='daq1_scalerdisplay11_title'>Scaler Display program</refentrytitle>
        <manvolnum>1daq</manvolnum>
    </refmeta>
    <refnamediv>
        <refname>ScalerDisplay</refname>
        <refpurpose>Display counts and rates in scalers.</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>
    <refsynopsisdiv>
        <cmdsynopsis>
            <command>
$DAQBIN/ScalerDisplay <replaceable>definition-file</replaceable>
            </command>            
        </cmdsynopsis>
        <literallayout>
Configuration file commands:

        </literallayout>
        <cmdsynopsis>
            <command>
channel <replaceable>?option...? name channel?.sourceid?</replaceable>
            </command>
        </cmdsynopsis>        
        <cmdsynopsis>
            <command>
page <replaceable>tabname page-title</replaceable>
            </command>
        </cmdsynopsis>        
        <cmdsynopsis>
            <command>
display_single <replaceable>tabname scaler-name</replaceable>
            </command>
        </cmdsynopsis>        
        <cmdsynopsis>
            <command>
display_ratio <replaceable>tabname numerator-scaler denominator-scaler</replaceable>
            </command>
        </cmdsynopsis>        
        <cmdsynopsis>
            <command>
blank <replaceable>tabname</replaceable>
            </command>
        </cmdsynopsis>        
        <cmdsynopsis>
            <command>
stripparam <replaceable>name</replaceable>
            </command>
        </cmdsynopsis>        
        <cmdsynopsis>
            <command>
stripratio <replaceable>numerator denominator</replaceable>
            </command>
        </cmdsynopsis>        
        <cmdsynopsis>
            <command>
stripconfig <replaceable>option ?...?</replaceable>
            </command>
        </cmdsynopsis>        
        
    </refsynopsisdiv>
    <refsect1>
        <title>DESCRIPTION</title>
        <para>
            The scaler display program displays scaler counts and rates
            during active data taking runs.   The environment variable
            <literal>SCALER_RING</literal> (See <literal>ENVIRONMENT VARIABLSE</literal> below)
            specifies the rings from which data will be taken.  A configuration file
            determines what is displayed and how.  
        </para>
        <para>
            The configuration file is described in the section <literal>CONFIGURATION FILE</literal>
            below.  The path to the configuration file is the one command line parameter that is both
            required and accepted by the scaler display program.
        </para>
        <para>
            The command synopsis assumes you have sourced the <filename>daqsetup.bash</filename> file
            into your shell.
        </para>
    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
        <title>CONFIGURATION FILE</title>
        <para>
            The configuration file is a Tcl script with a few command extensions.  The extensions
            provide the ability to associate a name with a scaler channel, and describe how and if that
            channel should be displayed.
        </para>
        <para>
            The display is organized into two sections.  A tabbed notebook at the top of the user interface
            provides several <firstterm>pages</firstterm>.  Each page is a table containing scaler names, rates, totals and,
            if appropriate, ratios of rates and totals for a pair of scalers.
            The lower section is an optional stripchart that shows the time evolution of counting rates
            in a scaler or the ratio of a pair of scaler rates.
        </para>
        <refsect2>
            <title>channel</title>
            <para>
                The <command>channel</command> command associates a name with a scaler channel from
                a data source.  The name is then used both to display the channel and to refer to
                it in other configuration file commands.  The form of this command is: 
            </para>
            <cmdsynopsis>
                <command>
channel <replaceable>?option...? name channel?.sourceid?</replaceable>                    
                </command>
            </cmdsynopsis>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><replaceable>option...</replaceable></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Are options that control how the channel is treated.
                            Legal options are:
                        </para>
                        <variablelist>
                            <varlistentry>
                                <term><option>-incremental</option> <replaceable>bool</replaceable></term>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>
                                        A boolean value which, if true, means that the
                                        scaler channel is incremental (cleared after each read).
                                        If false, the scaler counts are cumulative over the entire run.
                                    </para>
                                </listitem>
                            </varlistentry>
                            <varlistentry>
                                <term><option>-width</option> <replaceable>nbits</replaceable></term>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>
                                        The value is an integer that specifies the width of the scaler
                                        channel in bits.  All bits in positions higher than this value
                                        will be ignored.  This is primarily used with some CAMAC
                                        scalers read out through some interfaces that put additional
                                        bits in positions above bit <literal>23</literal>.
                                    </para>
                                </listitem>
                            </varlistentry>
                            <varlistentry>
                                <term><option>-lowlim</option> <replaceable>rate</replaceable></term>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>
                                        Specifies a low rate limit for the scaler.  If the count
                                        rate for this scaler drops below the specfied <replaceable>rate</replaceable>,
                                        the channel will show in a low rate alarmed status, if alarms are
                                        enabled via the checkbutton on the scaler display screen.
                                    </para>
                                </listitem>
                            </varlistentry>
                            <varlistentry>
                                <term><option>-hilim</option> <replaceable>rate</replaceable></term>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>
                                        Specifies a high rate limit for this scaler.
                                    </para>
                                </listitem>
                            </varlistentry>
                        </variablelist>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>name</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Is the name that will be given to the channel.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>channel</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Is the index into the data source's scaler array in which
                            the counts for this scaler live.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>sourceid</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            If supplied this specifies the source id from which the data
                            comes.  If not specified, the source id defaults no source id
                            which is what you get when the data has no body header.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
            
        </refsect2>
        <refsect2>
            <title>page</title>
            <para>
                The <command>page</command> command defines a new scaler display table page.
                It has the form:
            </para>
            <cmdsynopsis>
                <command>
page <replaceable>tabname page-title</replaceable>
                </command>
            </cmdsynopsis>        
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><replaceable>tabname</replaceable></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Is the text on the tab of the tabbed notebook in which the page is displayed.
                            This is also the name used to refer to this page in other
                            commands in the configuration file.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
        </refsect2>
        <refsect2>
            <title>display_single</title>
            <para>
                The <command>display_single</command> command appends a line to a page.
                The line displays the rates and total counts for a single scaler.
                The syntax of this command is:
            </para>
            <cmdsynopsis>
                <command>
display_single <replaceable>tabname scaler-name</replaceable>
                </command>
            </cmdsynopsis>        
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><replaceable>tabname</replaceable></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Is the name of the tab that has the page the line will be added to.  Lines
                            are added to the bottom of the page.  
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><replaceable>scaler-name</replaceable></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            The name of the scaler channel (as defined by  a
                            <command>channel</command> command) that will be displayed
                            on that line.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
            
        </refsect2>
        <refsect2>
            <title>display_ratio</title>
            <para>
                The display ratio command adds a line to a page that displays two
                scalers.  In additon the ratio of the rates and totals are displayed.
                The line is added to the end of the page.
                The syntax of this command is:
            </para>
            <cmdsynopsis>
                <command>
display_ratio <replaceable>tabname numerator-scaler denominator-scaler</replaceable>
                </command>
            </cmdsynopsis>        
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><replaceable>tabname</replaceable></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Is the label on the tab that is displaying the page
                            to which this line will be added.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><replaceable>numerator-scaler</replaceable></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Is the name of the scaler that will be the numerator of the
                            ratios.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><replaceable>denominator-scaler</replaceable></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Is the name of the scaler that will be the denominator of the ratios.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
        </refsect2>
        <refsect2>
            <title>blank</title>
            <para>
                Appends a blank line to the specified tab.  The syntax of this command is:
            </para>
            <cmdsynopsis>
                <command>
        
blank <replaceable>tabname</replaceable>
                </command>
            </cmdsynopsis>        
            
        </refsect2>
        <refsect2>
            <title>stripparam</title>
            <para>
                If no other strip chart traces have been defined, this enables the strip chart.
                The command also enables the plot of a single trace of the rate of the
                specified parameter on the strip chart.  The syntax of this command is:
            </para>
            <cmdsynopsis>
                <command>
stripparam <replaceable>name</replaceable>
                </command>
            </cmdsynopsis>        

        </refsect2>
        <refsect2>
            <title>stripratio</title>
            <para>
                If no other strip chart traces have been defined, this enables the strip chart.
                The command enables the plot of a trace that is the ratio of the numerator scaler
                to the denominator scaler.   The scalers are specified by the name they were given in
                their <command>channel</command> commands.
                The form of this command is:
            </para>
            <cmdsynopsis>
                <command>
stripratio <replaceable>numerator denominator</replaceable>
                </command>
            </cmdsynopsis>        

        </refsect2>
        <refsect2>
            <title>stripconfig</title>
            <para>
                Sets configuration options for the strip chart.  Naturally this is only meaningful
                if at least one trace is defined via the <command>stripparam</command> or
                <command>stripratio</command> commands above.
            </para>
            <para>
                The syntax of this command is:
            </para>
            <cmdsynopsis>
                <command>
stripconfig <replaceable>option ?...?</replaceable>
                </command>
            </cmdsynopsis>
            <para>
                The available options are:
            </para>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><option>-timeaxis</option> <replaceable>seconds</replaceable></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Number of seconds on the time axis.  Note that since the
                            plot is allowed to choose axis labels that are 'natural' you may
                            get slightly something a bit different, for example a value of
                            <literal>1198</literal> will almost certainly be modified to
                            <literal>1200</literal>.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
        </refsect2>
        
        
    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
        <title>ENVIRONMENT VARIABLES</title>
        <para>
            <literal>SCALER_RING</literal> is a space separated list of the
            ring URIs from which the program will acquire data.
        </para>
    </refsect1>
</refentry>


<!-- /manpage -->