<!-- chapter device-support -->
<chapter>
  <title>
    Mesytec MCFD-16 Controls 
  </title>

  <section>
    <title>Overview</title>

    <para>
      The Mesytec MCFD-16 is a 16-channel discriminator in the NIM form factor.
      Configuration of the device can be performed remotely over different
      communication protocols: usb and RC-bus. A GUI called MCFD16Control is
      provided as a part of NSCLDAQ to support communication with the device through both these
      protocols. A key feature is the ability to
      generate a tcl script capable of configuring the device with the same
      settings displayed in the GUI.
    </para>

    <para>
      The parameters that the GUI provides control over are the threshold,
      gain, width, dead time, delay, constant fraction, and polarity. All of
      these parameters
      can be set individually or commonly depending on the mode setting selected
      in the GUI. The interface reflects whether or not the device is being
      configured in either of these modes and prevents the setting of individual
      settings while in common mode. Doing so may not succeed and is therefore
      protected against. Finally, the GUI provides
      the ability to enable and disable channel pairs and to control the
      pulser. 
    </para>

    <para>
      It is important to know that the two different protocols sometimes accept different value
      ranges for the same parameter. One can see this by reading the manual
      and comparing the different ranges accepted for the gain setting in USB
      and RC-bus. To provide a unified user experience,
      the RC-bus ranges were chosen over the USB so if the user wants to refer
      to the manual, he/she should refer to the RC-bus section rather than the
      USB section.
    </para>

    <para>
      Finally, the control provided over the MCFD-16 through the GUI is made
      available through low-level drivers that can be used in any tclsh. The
      user can incorporate calls to these drivers in any script they want and
      can build input files to load into the GUI if desired. 
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Starting the GUI for USB communication</title>

    <para>
      To properly communicate over the USB protocol, the user should follow the
      the subsequent procedure. Before beginning, know that the device is
      particularly slow to respond over the USB protocol and so it is common for
      some bit of lag to exist when committing new parameters to the device.
    </para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Locate the name of the serial file that represents the MCFD-16 device.
          The serial file should be located in /dev with a name that begins with
          "ttyUSB". The number that forms the end of this file name is
          representative of the order in which the devices were plugged into the
          host computer. The number is therefore not unique and should be
          checked whenever the device is plugged in anew. Furthermore, ensure
          that this file is both readable and writable to your account. The
          spdaqs in the NSCL are configured to enforce these permissions.
        </para>
      </listitem> 

      <listitem>
        <para>
          At the command line, call 
        </para>
        <programlisting>
          MCFD16Control --protocol usb --serialfile your_serial_file
        </programlisting>

        <para>
          Doing so should bring up a window that looks like this.
        </para>
        <figure>
          <title>The MCFD16Control Graphical User Interface for USB</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/MCFD16Control-USBHowTo-0.png" align="center" format='PNG'/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          At this point, the user can manipulate the settings on the GUI safely
          without affecting the state of the device. Once the desired settings are
          configured, the user can commit those to the device by pressing the
          "Commit to Device" button. At the same time, if the user seeks to update
          the displayed settings from their device, he/she should press the
          "Update from Device" button. 
        </para> 
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Starting the GUI for the RC-bus through an MxDC device</title>

    <para>
      The set up for this is a bit more involved because it operates over the
      slow-controls server that is built into the VMUSBReadout program. 
    </para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
        The very first step is to connect the NIM busy output of the Mesytec
        digitizer (MADC-32, MTDC-32, or MQDC-32) to the MCFD-16 and to properly
        terminate the bus with 50 ohms.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          The next step is to set up the VMUSBReadout program to receive remote
          requests for the RC-bus. To do so, the user should add the following
          code to their ctlconfig.tcl script.
        </para>
        <programlisting>
          Module create mxdcrcbus myproxy
          Module config myproxy -base 0xffff0000
        </programlisting>

        <para>
          This causes a new slow controls module named "myproxy" to be loaded
          into the server that seeks to fulfull RC-bus requests through a device
          at base address 0xffff0000. Of course, this will only work when the
          device at the specified base address is a Mesytec family digitizer
          (MADC-32, MTDC-32, or MQDC-32). 
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          The user must next start up VMUSBReadout. This can be done by
          executing the ReadoutShell with VMUSBReadout registered as a data
          provider and then pressing the "Start" button. It can alternatively be
          accomplished by starting VMUSBReadout from the commmand-line. It
          really doesn't matter so long as VMUSBReadout is running. 
        </para>
        <para>
          By default, the slow-controls server will listen for connections on
          port 27000. This can be different if the host computer is running
          other programs that were listening on that port first. If the user
          suspects that the latter is the case, the port can be found by
          executing <code>lsof -i TCP</code> in a terminal. Find the row
          associated with your VMUSBReadout program by searching for the pid.
          The port being listened on will be listed in the right-hand column.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          With the slow-controls server up and running, the user can then go to
          a new shell and type:
        </para>

        <programlisting>
          MCFD16Control --protocol mxdcrcbus --module myproxy
        </programlisting>

        <para>
          By default, this assumes that the --host is localhost, --port is
          27000, and --devno is 0. The first two of these are probably correct
          unless other slow-controls servers are running. In which case, the
          user should determine the relevant information as described in the
          prior step. The device number (--devno) is the number of the device as
          it is identifiable by the RC-bus. For the MCFD-16, this is set via a
          switch on the back of the device.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          The user will then be presented with the following display and should
          control the parameters through the various widgets. The state of the
          GUI is not committed to the device until the "Commit to Device" button
          is pressed. If the user seeks to read the state of the device, the
          "Update from Device" button should be pressed. 
        </para>

        <figure id="mcfd16control_fig1">
          <title>MCFD16Control Graphical User Interface for MxDC-RCbus</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/MCFD16Control-MXDCRCBusHowTo-0.png" align="center" format='PNG'/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

  </section>

  <section>
    <title>
      Configuration menu
    </title>

    <para>
      To provide some extra configuration control of the device, there are a few
      specialized configuration dialogs that can be reached from the "Configure"
      drop down menu. They are described here.
    </para>

    <section>
      <title>Enable/Disable Channel</title>

      <para>
        The output for channels can be disabled in the MCFD-16. Support for this 
        feature is provided through the dialog at "Configure > Enable/disable..."
        It is important to realize that enabling and disabling a channel is done
        for channel pairs rather than individual channels. The same semantics apply 
        to this dialog for committing settings to the module as for the rest of
        the application. You must press "Commit" to transfer the state of the GUI to
        the module. You can read the state of the module by pressing the "Update" button.
        Each commit operation is always followed by an update operation intrinsically so
        that you can see whether a change succeeded or failed.
      </para>

      <figure id="mcfd16control_enabledisable_config">
        <title>Channel Enable/Disable Configuration Dialog</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/MCFD16Control-enabledisable-config-0.png" align="center" format='PNG'/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Configurable 16-Channel OR Trigger</title>

      <para>
        The MCFD-16 provides 3 trigger outputs that can be defined to emit
        signals defined by various logic internal to the device. NSCLDAQ supports
        setting two of these [trigger 0 (front panel output) and trigger 1 (back
        panel output)] to emit a configurable 16-channel OR. Each of these is
        configurable through the "Configure > Trigger OR..." menu. In the
        dialog, there are two columns labeled "OR Pattern 0" and "OR Pattern
        1". The OR Pattern 0 column configures the output for trigger 0 and the
        OR Pattern 1 column configures the output for trigger 1.  The same
        semantics hold for causing a change to the device as for the rest of
        the MCFD16Control application.  Changes to the GUI are not applied to
        the device until the "Commit to Device" button is pressed. If you want
        to update the GUI to reflect the state of the module, you should press
        the "Update From Device" button. Note that when you press "Commit to
        Device", the GUI will automatically follow the writes to the module
        with a read.  The read does the same thing as when you press "Update
        From Device".
      </para>

      <para>
        Another control accessible from this dialog is the ability to enable
        and disable the direct vetoing of the discriminators. This is referred
        to as the fast veto in the manual. Enabling this applies the veto to the
        discriminator stage of the module, which is before it reaches the logic
        for the trigger decision. It has been observed that if
        the veto associated with the OR pattern is disabled and the fast veto
        is enabled, there might still be some triggers when the input signal
        has a very fast rise time and the bandwidth limit setting is not
        enabled. The triggers are caused by nonlinearities in the amplfication
        stage of the MCFD-16. The moral of the story is that if you want to
        ensure that the trigger is not outputted when a veto is present, then
        you should not rely on the fast veto being enabled. Rather you should
        select the veto setting for the OR pattern you are concerned with.
      </para>

      <figure id="mcfd16control_orpattern_config">
        <title>OR Pattern Configuration Dialog</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/MCFD16Control-triggerOR-config-0.png" align="center" format='PNG'/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>
      Saving and restoring state
    </title>

    <section>
      <title>Saving the state</title>  
      <para>
        The state of the GUI can always be saved to a file by means of the "Save
        as..." and restored from file via the "Load..." menu options. Saving the state of the gui
        produces a tcl script that can be executed for configuring the device
        exactly as the GUI would display it. Note that this is not necessarily
        the state of the device itself, because the GUI and device are not
        necessarily identical unless settings are either committed or the gui is
        updated. To execute the script produced by the the GUI in a tclsh,
        the user must ensure:
      </para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The driver scripts are included in the TCLLIBPATH environment
            variable. These scripts should be usable if the user adds
            $DAQROOT/TclLibs to their TCLLIBPATH environment variable.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            The same settings for the communication protocol that were valid
            when the script was generated are still valid. In other words, if
            the GUI was launched with --protocol usb --serialfile /dev/ttyUSB0,
            then it must still be possible to write to the device through the
            /dev/ttyUSB0 file. The same idea must be true if the protocol was
            mxdcrcbus. If these have changed, the first few lines must be
            adjusted accordingly to instantiate the appropriate driver type.
            MCFD16USB types are used for usb communication and the MCFD16RC and
            MXDCRCProxy are used together for the mxdcrcbus. 
          </para>

          <programlisting>
            # USB instantiation and use example
            package require mcfd16usb
            MCFD16USB ::dev /dev/ttyUSB0
            ::dev SetThreshold 0 12
          </programlisting>

          <programlisting>
            # MxDC RC-bus instantiation and usage
            package require mcfd16rc
            MXDCRCProxy ::proxy -server localhost -port 27000 -module myproxy -devno 3
            MCFD16RC ::dev ::proxy
            ::dev SetThreshold 0 12
          </programlisting>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            At this point you can simply feed the script to a tclsh program. For
            example, executing a file called mysettings.tcl, you can do the
            following:
          </para>

          <programlisting>
            tclsh &lt; mysettings.tcl
          </programlisting>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Restoring the state</title>

      <para>
        Like saving, restoring implies that a setting is loaded to the GUI
        rather than immediately loading to the device. The user should select
        a tclscript that was either generated by the GUI through a save as
        operation or some other one that contains appropriate device driver
        calls. Loading the file causes the lines that are understood to be
        driver calls to be executed and loaded into the GUI. Furthermore, lines
        that set channel names (set ::MCFD16ChannelNames::chan0 name) are
        executed and read into the GUI. Other lines of code are not evaluated.
        it is important to note that this is not fully fool proof. It is
        important that the user refer to only one instance of a device driver
        in the script. For all of the parameters that are not set, the GUI will
        show "NA". It is possible to commit the state to the device when some
        parameters show "NA" because only valid parameters will actually affect
        the device. In other words, values that show "NA" are ignored during
        the commit.
      </para>
    </section>

  </section>

</chapter>

<!-- /chapter -->
